<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bar to free admission to the Lords Supper removed, or, A vindication of Mr. Humfreys free admission to the sacrament of the Lords Supper wherein the most materiall exceptions and objections of Doctor Drake against it in his book called A bar to free admission &amp;c. are taken off and answered : whereunto is annexed an expostulatory speech unto them of the Congragationall way : and also an examination of the book called A Scripture rail to the communion table, by some ministers in Glocester-shire / by John Timson.</title>
            <author>Timson, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 245 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 115 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25821</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09146329</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09146329</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42522</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42522)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1296:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bar to free admission to the Lords Supper removed, or, A vindication of Mr. Humfreys free admission to the sacrament of the Lords Supper wherein the most materiall exceptions and objections of Doctor Drake against it in his book called A bar to free admission &amp;c. are taken off and answered : whereunto is annexed an expostulatory speech unto them of the Congragationall way : and also an examination of the book called A Scripture rail to the communion table, by some ministers in Glocester-shire / by John Timson.</title>
                  <author>Timson, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 197, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Cotes and are to be sold by Will. Thompson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719. --  Humble vindication of a free admission to the sacrament of the Lord's Supper.</term>
               <term>R. D. --  (Roger Drake), 1608-1669. --  Bar against free admission to the Lord's Supper fixed.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42522:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42522:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BAR to Free Admiſſion TO THE <hi>LORDS-S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PPER</hi> REMOVED: OR, A Vindication of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys</hi> Free Admiſſion to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Wherein the moſt materiall Exceptions and Objections of Doctor <hi>Drake</hi> againſt it in his Book called <hi>A Bar to Free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> &amp;c. are taken off and anſwered.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed an expoſtulatory Speech unto them of the Congregationall way: And alſo an Examination of the Book called <hi>A Scripture Rail to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Table,</hi> by ſome Miniſters in <hi>Gloceſter ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN TIMSON a private Chriſtian of <hi>Great Bowden</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOH. 15.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ye are my friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Cotes</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Will. Tompſon</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Harborough,</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42522:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42522:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>COURTEOUS READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am neceſſitated not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to give thee ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement concerning the following diſcourſe, but alſo to make ſome Apologie for my ſelf in this my ſo bold un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, as this will be thought to be; and that perhaps even by ſome truly godly ſober Chriſtians and reverend Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; to whom it may ſeem unfit that ſuch a one as I ſhould inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in this Controverſie concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Admiſſion to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and that I ſhould undertake to make anſwer to a Reverend Doctor
<pb facs="tcp:42522:3"/>about theſe things. And therefore let me intreat thy patience, though I ſeem ſomewhat tedious in this Epiſtle by reaſon of the length of it. I truſt it will not be imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent nor unprofitable, but helping to the following diſcourſe, to free my ſelf from blame, and to help thee in the right underſtanding of what thou ſhalt read, and of my end and aime therein.</p>
            <p>The truth is, theſe few ſheets were not at firſt intended for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique view, but only to be ſent pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately to the reverend Doctor, that by the anſwer which I hoped he would return, my ſelf and ſome friends of mine might receive ſome ſatisfaction: but through the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of ſome others, to whom I imparted my thoughts herein, I am now overcome &amp; perſwaded to make them publique; but with great diſadvantage, not having time to
<pb facs="tcp:42522:3"/>perfect and amplifie things ſutable to ſo different an end from what I firſt intended. And I confeſſe I have not ſo heedfully kept to the Doctors expreſſions, nor writen arguments with that latitude or fulneſſe, nor kept to his method orderly as he goes on in anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Humfrey,</hi> as I ſhould and would have done, if my intent at firſt had been to appear in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique. But yet I have been as carefull as I could in taking his ſenſe, and have not omitted any thing of moment, which I had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to inſert and anſwer in my own method and way which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to my ſelf at firſt.</p>
            <p>And for Mr. <hi>Humfreys</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I have made but little uſe of them, more out of haſte then out of any diſſenting from him; and chuſing rather to adde to what he hath aſſerted and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:42522:4"/>evinced, then to repeat his own: becauſe I have an earneſt deſire that this controverſie may be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſifted and more throughly ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched into; it being of greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment then moſt even of thoſe that are godly have or do judge it to be, for the ending of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſtractions and diviſions in this unſetled Church. Our being diſſatisfied about Sacramental com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, hath been the great oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and inſtrumentall cauſe of our confuſions and diſorders ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Churches deſtruction. If ſatisfaction can but be given in the warrant of free Admiſſions, I conceive the only inſtrumentall cauſe of the Churches unſetled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will be removed; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will much hinder the falling in of Presbyterians and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents into one way of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſcipline, eſpecially the
<pb facs="tcp:42522:4"/>orthodox party of both. And as for thoſe that deny our Baptiſme, Church and Miniſtry, as Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, there is little hope of gaining their return. I deſire it may be put to ſome ſolemn and ſerious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate impartially; For although the principles committed to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in the enſuing diſcourſe, be ſomewhat againſt the common ſtream, yet I have ſome hope they may be a means to diſcover ſome common miſtakes, with ſuch glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering of rationall and Scripture light, as better heads may make to ſhine more bright in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world. I look to be cenſured for this my preſumption in diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the common interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſeverall Scriptures; and aſſerting ſome things againſt the judgement of many or moſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines and godly Chriſtians, who will be ready to object againſt me
<pb facs="tcp:42522:5"/>and charge me with a fault herein; againſt which give me leave to make ſome defence.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by confeſſing that this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing of diſſenting from ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned and godly, hath been a greater barre in my way, then any ground of Scripture or ſtrength of argument I ever heard or have ſeen from any godly man. And were the Church in a well ordered ſetled ſtate, I had rather choſen in ſome leſſer things to erre with the Church, then dare to do any thing that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght break the peace and order of the ſame. But in an unſetled diſorderly condition of the Church as it is now with us; all things in the Church being now upon the brinck of confuſion and ruine; it concerns even every private mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to ſhew himſelf, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute his mite toward the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the whole. In vain
<pb facs="tcp:42522:5"/>do we look to have the effects and conſequences, our diviſions, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings and ſeparations to ceaſe, while the moſt ſober and godly nouriſh them in their riſe and cauſe. The ſame principles maintained by the godly in the Biſhops times, would as neceſſarily have run us into the ſame ſeparations and diviſions, had not the ſeverity of diſcipline put a reſtraint to our exceſſe from the ſame or like miſtakes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I deny that this free admiſſion pleaded for, is altogether novell or a new thing. For did not our firſt reformers maintain a free Admiſſion, nay command a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall obſervance of the Supper of the Lord three times in the year at leaſt, under ſome puniſhment to be inflicted for unneceſſary neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect; grounded (I conceive) from the equity of the Law of the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, <hi>Numb.</hi> 9. and the command
<pb facs="tcp:42522:6"/>of Jeſus Chriſt: Do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me. And will any ſay that our firſt reformers were not godly and learned men? It's true they urged it not till Church mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers were of years of diſcretion, and not under Church cenſure; and required that all ſhould learn the Lords Prayer, the Creed, and the Ten Commandements, &amp;c. which would be now eaſily yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to, in order to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, do not Proteſtant god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writers, in all reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, maintain infant Baptiſme up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Covenant relation, in that the children of Chriſtians by birth pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, are really members of the Church; and ſo eſteemed to be as truly as thoſe that by nature are aliens, and admitted upon their profeſſion of faith? And is not there the ſame reaſon for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment
<pb facs="tcp:42522:6"/>of the other Sacrament of the Supper, being of years, and already admitted members? ſhould not theſe have as much priviledge as thoſe that come in as proſelytes or Diſciples by preaching of the Word? Where do we finde that any were received to Baptiſme, and yet denied the Supper? or what eſſentiall difference is there between Baptiſme and the holy Supper, that the ſame profeſſion that fits for the one, will not ſerve for the other, being perſons of years? The Bloud of Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified is repreſented in both for remiſſion of ſins, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. And by conſent of all, both ſeal to the ſame Covenant, in which the unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, as well as the regenerate, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and concerned; and that as well when grown to years, as in their minority: they adhering to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary means of grace as wel as others,
<pb facs="tcp:42522:7"/>that they may obtain the bleſſings of the Covenant promiſed and ſealed by the Sacrament. And I think the wofull conſequences, and runnings out into ſuch exorbitances amongſt the godly in theſe times, may make intelligent and ſober men ſenſible of their own incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtences and interfeering in things concerning the Sacraments. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the unregenerate in the Church not baptized till grown to years, could that diſcovenant or diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, it not being their own fault, but the fault of their parents? might not ſuch challenge their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of that Church in which they were born members, by vertue of that memberſhip meerly? their memberſhip not being an effect or conſequent of Baptiſm, but Baptiſm a conſequent priviledge of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip: though I confeſſe it's true of aliens, they are formally inſtalled
<pb facs="tcp:42522:7"/>into memberſhip in the Church by Baptiſme upon their profeſſion of faith.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, did not all godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in the Biſhops time, that were for conformity, adminiſter the Sacrament to all, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding any? and ſhall we judge that they practiſed againſt their judgement and conſcience?</p>
            <p>Miſtake me not, good Reader, whoſoever thou art, as if I did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge, or labour to foſter any in their groſſe ignorance, by the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe or any thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; or the ſloth and not profiting under the means; or that I plead for a diſpenſation for the profane and ſcandalous in the Church: poor creatures! they ſhall know it one day to their coſt (if they repent not) what it is to abuſe the grace of holy adminiſtrations, and to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the means of their ſalvation.
<pb facs="tcp:42522:8"/>God will be ſanctified by or in all he admits to come neer him; and all his holy ordinances are a ſweet ſavour to him, in them that periſh as well as in them that are ſaved in the uſe thereof.</p>
            <p>Moſt terrible things are written of them that have the light and walk in darkneſſe; that have the means to know and do, and yet will not, but remain both ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and diſobedient to the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt. Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full will be the doom of all thoſe that have had their reſidence at the feaſt of fat things of the Goſpell, and ſhall be found without the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment at the laſt. Therefore I ſhall deſire and intreat all to take heed of this, and to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to thoſe that are over them in the Lord; as to them that are appointed by Jeſus Chriſt to watch over their ſouls, as they that muſt
<pb facs="tcp:42522:8"/>give account thereof. I ſay, let me perſwade you to be willing to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, catechized and tried: refuſe no means that tends to your edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, inſtruction and ſalvation, I beſeech you: I know your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and unanſwerable walking to the rules of the Goſpell is ſuch, that moſt are unwilling to go to their Miniſter to be examined and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed in private, in order to the Sacrament. I, but remember you muſt be brought to a ſtricter ſearch and account before you can be ſaved: And if you be unwilling to give an account of your faith and hope that is in you to your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that would incourage you in your Chriſtian profeſſion; and take ſuch advantages to inſtruct you and confirm you in the grounds and practiſe of Chriſtianity; what would you do, if a perſecuting enemy to the Proteſtant Religion
<pb facs="tcp:42522:9"/>ſhould put you upon the renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the true Religion, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Turk or Papiſt; or elſe be put to death; as hath been a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lot of the profeſſors of the Chriſtian Religion in moſt ages ſince the coming of Chriſt? Oh be not ſuch ſtrangers to your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours that labour among you; what ſhall they be appointed to bring your ſouls to heaven, and will you not acquaint them with your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and other wants and doubts which are impediments in your way? Would you be more frequent, friendly and familiar with your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, you would not be afraid to have conference with them in things concerning Gods Kingdome and the good of your own ſouls. Let not (good Reader) ſhame of thy ignorance, hinder thee from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting thy ſelf to be proved and taught in order to the Sacrament.
<pb facs="tcp:42522:9"/>For ignorance continued in under the means of knowledge is damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Barren branches of the true vine ſhall be cut off and burned. Remember the barren fig-tree. Though as yet thy profiting hath not been anſwerable to the coſt and charge God hath been at, or his grace, mercy, goodneſſe and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence toward thee do require; yet now let the patience and goodneſſe of God, ſo long abuſed, lead thee to repentance, and inquiring after him. Let not ſenſe of thine own ignorance make thee rather forbear the Sacrament, then go to thy Miniſter to be better informed: but rather implead thy right, and come and do thy homage and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice as well as thou canſt, though not ſo well as thou ſhouldſt. Put caſe thou be judged unfit to come to the Sacrament; yet follow on, doubling thy deſires and endevours
<pb facs="tcp:42522:10"/>to receive as farre as thou canſt. If thou be deſired to forbear untill the next Sacrament, let it humble thee, but not diſcourage thee; that being better prepared, thou mayeſt expect a greater bleſſing. But if thou art beat off with delaies, wait and be aſpectator of thy bleeding Saviour, ſet forth crucified before thine eyes by inſtituted ſignes of Bread and Wine: and if thou maiſt not take and eat in remembrance that Chriſts bloud was ſhed for many for remiſſion of ſins, and to ſave ſinners by giving them grace and glory; yet let me perſwade thee to give thy preſence, to hear and ſee in that remembrance: thou knoweſt not but that the ſight of ſuch an object, the effect of love and bleeding bowels may melt thy heart, and draw thy ſoul after him thy mercifull Redeemer, it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy fault thou doeſt not actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:42522:10"/>receive. Be it ſo that thou art ſtill repulſed, as like to eat and drink judgement to thy ſelf; yet let not that affright thee from the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Chriſt, ſo long as thou art art a viſible ſubject in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Plead thy duty and homage, how thou art obliged to Chriſt in this obſervance: and ſay, thou art ſo well perſwaded of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt in all that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his ſubjects, that thou wilt humbly venture upon his mercy, in doing thy duty as thou art able. But I ſhall commend thee to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing diſcourſe for further know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy duty, and pleading thy right, during thy priviledge of poſitive Church memberſhip.</p>
            <p>And in the laſt place I ſhall in all humility offer a few words to the reverend Miniſters of God, as a means to quench the preſent flames that are in the Church of Chriſt in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42522:11"/>
            <p>Firſt, let me beſeech you not to urge upon your people any practiſe under neceſſity of duties of worſhip, either publique or private, that is not evidently commanded, or at leaſt deducted from the clear and genuine ſenſe of holy Scripture by neceſſary, conſequence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, labour ſo to agree among your ſelves in the main eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentials of Doctrine, Worſhip and Diſcipline, that in every place there may be a preaching and holding forth of the ſame things in all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, condeſcend to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of your people, with an equall reſpect in all your miniſteriall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, both publique and private, that none may be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, nor any indulged in an evill way.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, be as watchfull of thoſe that are inclined to an inordinate zeal in the ſmaller matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb facs="tcp:42522:11"/>as of thoſe that expreſſe but little zeal at all in Gods worſhip.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, allow the worſt of your people the title of Chriſtians, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, members, and allow them all other externall priviledges which of right are theirs in regard of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative ſtate, as they are ſuch: yet deal faithfully with them, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching their reall ſtate in order to their eternall weal or woe.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, decline (as much as may be) novelty and variety in profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, catechiſmes, and all eſſentials of publique worſhip; that your people may more willingly adhere to you, and give you the greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to advance the Chriſtian Religion among them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, What in you lies reſtore with the ſpirit of meekneſſe, in your private admonitions, weak brethren, that through infirmity fall; &amp; do not exaſperate any w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> pulpit invections,
<pb facs="tcp:42522:12"/>unleſſe it be in caſe of known obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy. But I ſhall leave all to your charitable conſtruction and ſober apprehenſion of what I do here of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to your conſideration. I am a poor worm, and look to be deſpiſed for medling with things out of my ſpheare: but I ſee it's the common lot of the moſt learned in theſe times to be reproached, and therefore I ſhall the better bear it; though for this my vindicating of Mr. <hi>Humfrey</hi> from reproach, I be the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached: I am ſorry his principles be not vindicated from the reverend Doctors exceptions and objections by a better pen then his,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Who is thy humble ſervant, breathing after the ſimplicity of truth, <hi>John Timſon.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42522:12"/>
            <head>The Barre to free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the LORDS S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PPER removed.</head>
            <p>MEEting with a Book called <hi>A Barre to free Admiſſion to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> written by Doctor <hi>Drake,</hi> in anſwer to Mr. <hi>Humphrey,</hi> and having diligently read both, I finde that even good men are too apt to reprove one another in things controverted betwixt them; which ought not ſo to be. As for Mr. <hi>Humphreys</hi> vindication of free ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion (as he ſtates, bounds and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles it) it ſeems to me more rationall and clear, then to deſerve ſo many harſh expreſſions from the reverend Doctor, as he hath let ſlip; whether in haſte, or more deliberately, I leave to himſelf to conſider. Sure I am, ſome words might better have been ſpared, then ſo publiſhed in print to the world,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42522:13"/>it being not yet determined whether Mr. <hi>Humphreys</hi> diſcourſe be untrue or no, though diſputable with the Doctor (it ſeems) <hi>whether it be more full of words or untruthes,</hi> which is very uncharitable and unbrotherly dealing; but I forbear. Both the reverend Doctor and Mr. <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prey</hi> are Gentlemen I am altogether unacquainted with, whoſe gifts &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned abilities I yet much reverence, and wiſh this poor diſtracted Church may never want ſuch officers to rule and feed her in the Lord, as the meaneſt of them be. It's an unhappy controverſie I confeſſe, and little cauſe there is to take content in theſe debates: yet as times are, it hath need of ſcanning and ſifting; becauſe much of the unity and welbeing of the nationall Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the right ſtating and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this Queſtion; our doubts and ſcruples concerning the holy Supper, having upon the matter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled all. Some miſtakes about admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereto, have run thouſands into faction, ſchiſme, and ſeparation, under a zeal of ſeparating the Precious from the Vile, of withholding the childrens bread from dogs, of preſerving the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances pure, &amp;c. The premiſes are good,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42522:13"/>conducing much to reformation, were they not miſapplyed in reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and in reſpect of the right way, and means of putting them in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as things now ſtand, as I beleeve it will appear they are, by this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe; wherein I ſhall ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to vindicate that little Tract of Mr. <hi>Humphrey</hi> from the Doctors un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brotherly dealing with him, according to my meaſure and meanneſſe. Not that I intend an orderly and exact reply to every particular (which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my capacity nor occaſions of my laborious calling will bear) but to undermine his chiefeſt ſtrength, paſſing by the reſt.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all, for the Text which Mr. <hi>Humphrey</hi> delivers his diſcourſe upon, though he may be thought not ſo happy in his choice of it in order to what he inſiſteth on, (as having ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſound then a true and full ſenſe of the queſtion and point concluded) yet I doubt not but the diſcourſe will (as to the ſubſtance thereof) be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by other Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Judas</hi> his receiving or not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, I look not upon it as clearly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42522:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42522:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42522:15"/>one way or other. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I think that firſt preſident, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſupply of other Scriptures, would make much for or againſt us in this matter, they being Apoſtles only that then received, whoſe office in the Church is now ceaſed.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, I ſhall not go about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend every quotation or aſſertion in Mr. <hi>H.</hi> Book, nor to clear him from ſome inconſiſtences pointed out by the reverend Doctor; it's ſufficient that he hath made good the main thing aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: namely, <hi>That all Church members of years, and under Church indulgence (not rightly excommunicated) may come freely to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His free Admiſſion is limited with exceptions of infants, diſtracted, the excommunicated, and he might ſay, the drunk.</p>
            <p>Now the Doctor ſaith, <hi>That by the ſame reaſon that he excepts theſe, we may may except the groſly ignorant and ſcandalous in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning which this twofold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry is made.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether Church members of years, having the exerciſe of reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42522:15"/>ignorant, be as uncapable of the Sacrament as Infants or diſtraught?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether ſcandalous members un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Church indulgence, may be equally debarred this Church priviledge with the regularly excommunicated?</p>
            <p>To the former of theſe the Doctor ſaith, <hi>That the groſly ignorant are as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to examine themſelves, and diſcerne the Lords body as Infants, and therefore as juſtly to be excepted againſt: nay more, becauſe Infants and diſtraught may have the grace of the covenant really, the other not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer; what the ſecret working of the Spirit may be in ſuch comes not within the Churches cogniſance to inquire, but what is agreeable to the revealed will of God; and then if any of years, being baptized &amp; profeſſing the true religion be in the ſame incapacity as Infants or diſtracted; it's true there is the ſame exception againſt them, otherwiſe not. For mine own part, I never knew any of years but could take and eat and drink of the conſecrated ſignes reverently and orderly according to the inſtitution, as to the externals of that ſervice, which the ſtate of Infants is uncapable of.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42522:16"/>
            <p>And mad men would indanger the abuſe of the holy ſignes, by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent and unreverent demeanour in thoſe neceſſary acts of communion and worſhip. And it muſt be granted that perſons at years are not under that naturall incapacity that infants are, in order to the outward form of worſhip, Neither are Infants as ſuch under the obligation of precepts of worſhip, as grown perſons in the Church are. Nor can it be reaſonably imagined, that ſuch a ſtate of perſons in the Church ſhould be admitted actually to receive, that in the diſcretion of the Church are no proper objects of Church cenſures, in point of offending, which grown perſons in the Church are though never ſo ignorant. And what though the Doctor ſay, <hi>he can teach a childe of three or four years old, as much or more then ſome of our people at years have learned all their life time?</hi> A Parrat may be taught to ſpeak words: but can he make ſuch children rationally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what they are taught, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe devotion from a principle of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in reference to religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? as in charity we may hope of grown ones according to that little
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42522:16"/>they know; which may be conceived by their deſires after it, and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour in the Sacramentall actions. Moreover, I doubt not but the Doctor or any other Miniſter of the Goſpell, may in a ſhort time, inform the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant among their people, ſo as to make them capable of diſcerning the Lords body; and to eat and drink lawfully, in the Apoſtles ſenſe, though not in the ſenſe I ſhall give account of hereafter. All which being laid together, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Church members of years moſt ignorant are not ſo uncapable of the Sacrament, as Infants or mad men are: and therefore the ſame or like ground of excepting againſt the one, will not equally reach the other. And then the Doctors often retorting Mr. <hi>H.</hi> exception, doth rather diſcover weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then adde any ſtrength to the cauſe. This to the firſt inquiry.</p>
            <p>As for the other, namely, whether the ſcandalous members under Church indulgence, may be equally debarred this Church priviledge with the regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly excommunicated, I do not finde the Doctors judgement ſo expreſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered: but he ſeems to debar ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42522:17"/>from the Sacrament. But ſure to debar Church members ſcandalous their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall priviledge during Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, and toleration, they being under triall or otherwiſe, is contrary to the judgement and practiſe of the independent Churches, and ſeems ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationall and unjuſt to execute before a judiciall triall and ſentence.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe I am unſatisfied with their proceedings (as Presbytered) toward Church members of years admitted.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They ſet up an Elderſhip whoſe office is very doubtfull, too doubtfull to aſſume and exerciſe the keyes of Chriſts Kingdome (eſpecially where there is no aſſociation of Churches) ſo that upon the matter the power of ſentence is in the Paſtour alone, or in thoſe whom Jeſus Chriſt never im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered with the keys at all to binde and looſe authoratively.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They ſet up ſuch a way of triall and Church examination of native Church members in order to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (the obſervance whereof is both their duty and their priviledge) as no word doth warrant, diſcouraging the moſt from indevouring after their duty
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42522:17"/>and priviledge; ſo that upon the matter they are left out without any regular caſting out.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They cauſe a careleſſe forbearance of the Sacrament; and make their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſion and excommunication upon the matter all one; and the Doctor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes all preſence at every ordinance, denying only the act of receiving to the worſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They poſitively ſuſpend Church members for ignorance and ſuch like wants and comings ſhort of what they ſhould be to God; for which there is not the leaſt warrant, either of rule or preſident, in divine writ.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They make excommunication leſſe then it is indeed, in allowing the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate preſence in the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at every ordinance: and make it more then indeed it is, in diſmembring Church members by it, it being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as the laſt remedy to heal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed members, not to deſtroy them. They are not thereby diſmembred, but to be lookt upon (ſaith Mr. <hi>Cawdry</hi>) as diſeaſed members under cure.</p>
            <p n="6">6. No more priviledge is allowed to Church members not approved of by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42522:18"/>the elderſhip (though not yet under any poſitive ſentence) then is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Heathens: and to the excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate as much of priviledge in the ordinances of the Church is allowed as to Heathens. All which upon triall will be found to be beſide the rule, I think: and yet ſuch are the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that flow from the Doctors own principles and premiſes, in his Bar to free admiſſion to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>In the next place, the Doctor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his judgement concerning a ſcandalous member of a congregation impresbytered preſuming to receive: what is to be done in ſuch a caſe: <hi>As firſt, the Miniſter is to tell him of the ſinne, and deſire him to forbear; if that will not do, then to ſhew him the preſent danger of murdering Chriſt, and eating and drinking judgement to himſelf, and he hath done his duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then it may be inquired, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he mean only in caſe of common fame, the ſcandall having been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: otherwiſe, I ſuppoſe it will not be a time to nominate any members ſinne, or perſon in publique firſt.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:42522:18"/>
            <p>Then ſecondly, I queſtion whether a ſcandalous member doth neceſſarily murder Chriſt, and eat and drink judgement to himſelf in the Scripture ſenſe, whether the perſon be regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate or unregenerate: For he may be Scandalous, and yet knowing, and able to put a difference between com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bread and the inſtituted ſigns, in order to their end. He might be drunk the week before, and yet ſober, ſcrious and reverent in the act of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, and not guilty of the body and bloud of Chriſt, nor eat and drink judgement to himſelf in the Doctors ſenſe.</p>
            <p>He often diſtinguiſhes of worthy Church members and unworthy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the judgement of viſibility; accounting the regenerate in the Church only worthy of admittance, but not the other, they not having a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall worthineſſe, muſt neceſſarily eat and drink unworthily, and ſo judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to themſelves in the Apoſtles ſenſe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe all his concluſions ſeem to be deducted from meer miſtakes and miſapplyings of the Apoſtles ſenſe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42522:19"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20, to the 34. to the great perill and danger of the viſible Church of Chriſt, as cauſing rents and diviſions therein, I ſhall therefore make bold to preſent to conſideration theſe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry queries in reference to a diſcovery of the moſt probable ſenſe of the place, humbly praying the Reader (when ever he think of me) to think ſeriouſly and impartially of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Enquiry is to be made whether the Apoſtle intends any ſuch thing as perſonall worthineſſe, or unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in order to the Sacrament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether the unworthineſſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks to, were not meerly their miſcarriages and actuall offending in or about the externals of Sacramentall actions and order.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What were thoſe ſins that provok'd the Lord ſo immediately to puniſh them for the preſent, and made them liable to be further puniſhed for the future.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether they were chaſtiſed for unworthineſſe of perſon or other ſins they were guilty of, before they came together to celebrate the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:42522:19"/>
            <p n="5">5. What is the remedy the Apoſtle preſcribes to that Church to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent future judgement, and to enjoy preſent benefit.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether the unregenerate and moſt ignorant perſon profeſſing and owning the true Religion among them, were not in a capacity ſo to uſe the remedy, as to prevent the judgement and receive benefit by the ordinance where God gave a bleſſing.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether the duty of ſelf-examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in order to the Sacrament is not to be reſtrained to the premiſes treated on in the context.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether a careleſſe neglect or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacity of this duty of ſelf-examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before, do excuſe and give a writ of eaſe from that precept of publique duty and ſervice, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether there be any thing in the inſtitution, nature, end, language, acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sacrament in the context, or elſewhere, incongruous to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the unregenerate in the Church.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but an ingenuous anſwer to theſe Queries would much moderate
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42522:20"/>the unchriſtian rigour of theſe times about Sacramentall communion, if not to make the controverſie to ceaſe among ſober godly men. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pardon my boldneſſe in adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to preſent to publick view my confuſed apprehenſions in anſwer to theſe queries, and that with as much brevity as I can. Something muſt be done; and if I can diſcover the truth or give occaſion unto ſome more able to doe it, I ſhall bleſſe God, and think my labour well beſtowed.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, I conceive there is not the leaſt hint or ſound of unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of perſons in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> ſpoken to by the Apoſtle, in reference to the Sacrament, nor are they blamed or puniſhed for their reall unworthineſſe as to God, viſible to the Church, though it's probable they had ſuch amongſt them in that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. For in the beginning of this Epiſtle, the Apoſtle gives them the titles of <hi>the Church of God, ſanctified in Chriſt Juſus, called to be Saints, &amp;c.</hi> And of thoſe that were puniſhed for profaning the ordinance, the Apoſtle ſpeaks very hopefully, nay confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42522:20"/>that their perſons were juſtified; they were chaſtened of the Lord that they might not be condemned with the world.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſaid,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> The Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> were all of them, at leaſt viſibly, worthy in reſpect of their perſons; and therefore their free admiſſion is no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for us, ſeeing many of ours want that viſible worthineſſe. And if thoſe that were viſibly worthy, did through their miſcarriage eat judgement to themſelves, what may we think of ours, that have not ſo much as that viſible worthineſſe which they had?</p>
            <p n="1">1. I anſwer,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
               </label> If there be nothing againſt perſonall unworthineſſe in perſons profeſſing the true religion, in the context, in order to the Sacrament, then unworthineſſe of perſon in ſuch can be no bar againſt them: but the former is true, therefore the latter is true alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Apoſtle upon ſo weighty occaſion meddle not with their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe of perſon, in reference to their receiving, then neither need we to meddle with it: it is ſufficient that thoſe we admit be baptized, and of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42522:21"/>true Religion, under Church indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, to entitle them to all the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which they are to uſe as means of their ſpirituall good; they being given to the viſible Church to that very end.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If our Baptiſme were rightly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred according to the Word, then ours of years that are of the ſame with them of the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> have as much externall priviledge in the Church, as they had, till either by Apoſtaſie they fall off, or by the right exerciſe of Diſcipline they be put out. And had we the ſame charity the Apoſtle had, we would allow them the title of Saints, beleevers, brethren by profeſſion and calling, as they did all along.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond and third Quere, I am ſure the Text is clear for the affirmative, namely, that their unworthineſſe was meerly their miſcarriages and actuall offending about the externals of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall actions and order.</p>
            <p>And they did eat and drink unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, not diſcerning the Lords body, and they profaned the holy Ordinance, in that they put no difference between
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42522:21"/>their own ſupper and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; their own bread and the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſigns: And for perſons to make the conſecrated ſigns, appointed by Jeſus Chriſt to ſpirituall ends (as in the inſtitution) a common or civill thing, to pleaſe and ſatisfie the outward man, muſt needs be a great evill; and was that high and provoking ſin for which they are there puniſhed, as well they might. For indeed it was a ſin worſe then carrying the Arke of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant contrary to order; and yet for that the Lord made a breach upon them. And <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for offering ſtrange fire which the Lord commanded not: ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a thing it is not to come up to, or to adde to, or to profane divine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions. Doubtleſſe the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were very rude, unreverent and diſorderly in the preſent obſervance; ſome were hungry, and ſome drunk; ſome had too much, and others could get none, or but little, as is intimated in the remedy or direction given to that particular caſe: To tarry one for another (as to order) and if any hunger, let him eat at home, &amp; not make the holy Supper a meer bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42522:22"/>of eating and drinking; that they come not together to condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for time to come, as they had done before.</p>
            <p>To the fourth Query, I anſwer, They were not chaſtened for unworthineſſe of perſon, or for any other ſins they were guilty of before, but for unworthy actings in the act of receiving, or at that time. <hi>For this cauſe ſome are weak, and ſome are ſick, and ſome are fallen aſleep,</hi> that is, for eating and drinking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, contrary to order and decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: the which word <hi>unworthily,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects their manner of doing, not their perſons. It's no were ſaid, Whoſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and drinketh being unworthy, is guilty of the body and bloud of the Lord. And I think it is no where elſe the language of Scripture to require reall worthineſſe of perſon, before they be ſit to come under precepts of duty and ſervice. Doth not Baptiſme lay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements upon all to obſerve all the commands of Chriſt?
<note place="margin">Mat 28.19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>And do this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me,</hi> is a precept for the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized of years to obſerve (they being under Church indulgence) otherwiſe we ſhall be driven to queſtion our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42522:22"/>and then our Church miniſtry; and run mad to the ſeparations, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin again if we could tell how.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, how injurious to Church members doth our ungrounded rigour, and private interpretations cauſe us to be!</p>
            <p>To the fift Querie, I ſay, The reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is both by inſtruction and direction, by theſe waies the Apoſtle applies him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to them for the cure of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie. He repeats the firſt inſtitution, comments upon it, the better to give them to underſtand the nature, end and uſe of the ordinance, which before they were ignorant of, or did not well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider. And having taught them the minde of Chriſt, in what was neceſſary to that ſervice, then he gives direction what they muſt doe. Firſt to examine themſelves, whether they underſtand what theſe things of God did mean, as they had been taught; and then to tarry one for another, that the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance may be carryed on with order, decency and reverence, becoming wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and then he aſſures them they ſhall not be judged of the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:42522:23"/>
            <p>To the ſixth Querie, I anſwer, The Apoſtle intends the remedy to the good of the whole Church, which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends every particular member of years that did actually receive, and offend therein. And he taught them not any thing, but what was eaſie to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by any reaſonable man owning the true Religion among them. He directed them not to do any thing, but what was eaſie for them to do external<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And their offending was ſo obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and apparent, that they were eaſily convinced, and yeelded to the reproofe, Gods bleſſing concurring with the means: and indeed we read no more of their offending in that manner af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards; nor any other Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>But they were a Church conſiſting of members under better qualifications then ours;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> therefore the ſame remedy which was ſufficient for them, is not ſufficient for moſt of ours.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, The Apoſtle writing to them, That if any man that is called a brother, be a fornicator, or covetous, or an idolater, or a railer, or a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, or an extortioner, with ſuch they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42522:23"/>ſhould not eat; intimates, that there were ſuch among them that were as bad as ours.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, if we be a true Church, &amp; our members we admit true Church members, even as theirs, then ours come under the ſame rules with them; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we can finde different rules for the ſame Church in the ſame things and reſpects: if not, then ours are under the ſame rule in reference to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (untill they be legally ejected and caſt out) and are bound to act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thoſe rules, and that order preſcribed, in hope of a bleſſing, even the worſt member among us.</p>
            <p>To the ſeventh Querie, whether the duty of ſelf-examination in order to the ſacrament be not properly to be reſtrained to the premiſes treated on in the context; I anſwer, That whether it be to be extended in this place ſo farre as moſt do urge, in reſpect of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſtate unto God, competent meaſure of knowledge in the many fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of Religion, the having and acting every grace neceſſary to ſalvation, &amp;c. or to be reſtrained to the particulars
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42522:24"/>there mentioned; I dare not perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily determine, though ſtrongly incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to beleeve the latter. Not becauſe I think ſelf-examination touching the former may careleſly be neglected by any; but I queſtion whether the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle had any reſpect thereto in this place, in reference to the Sacrament: becauſe I conceive the Apoſtle here ſutes the remedy to the malady; and that unworthineſſe of perſon was not any part of malady nor ignorance in the fundamentals of Religion; but their not diſcerning the Lords body, and that put them upon other unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy carriages, as is ſhewed before. And therefore as examination is part of the remedy preſcribed, it ſeems to me, moſt probable, that it properly refers to the rule of inſtitution, and thoſe other directions given in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text.</p>
            <p>The eighth Querie is, whether a careleſſe neglect of this private duty of ſelf-examination before, do give a writ of eaſe, and excuſe ſuch negligent perſons from the precept of publique duty and ſervice, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:42522:24"/>
            <p>To this I ſay, I cannot conceive how the neglect of a private duty, can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe any in the neglect of publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that are Church members of years, under the obligation of all that Chriſt commands. The Apoſtles being ſent to preach and baptize thoſe that received their Doctrine (the Doctrine of the Goſpell) and came under the baptiſme of Chriſt, were bound to teach them to obſerve all things whatſoever Chriſt had commanded; and in ſo doing they had a promiſe of his preſence, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon their endevours, <hi>And loe I am with you alwaies to the end of the world, Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. What can be more plain, except we ſhall ſay the obſervance of the holy Supper, is none of his commands?</p>
            <p>I think Chriſt commands nothing for the hurt of his viſible ſubjects, they obſerving it according to their preſent capacity. Can an inſtance be given in the Old or New Teſtament, of any that came under Circumciſion or Baptiſme, whether proſelyte or native of years, that as private members were admitted to all other ordinances in the Church; and yet were forbidden the uſe of the other Sacrament, the Paſſover or the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42522:25"/>Lords Supper? There is but one Law for the ſtranger and home-borne. If our Baptiſme be the Baptiſme of Chriſt, I ſay, if it be the baptiſme of Chriſt, by which we are conſecrated to Chriſt, why ſhould any be exempted from any obedience and priviledge, being of years, and under Church indulgence at leaſt, more then the circumciſed under <hi>Moſes,</hi> or the Baptized under the Apoſtles? Our not acting according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture preſidents in this particular, will (I fear) in time unchurch us. We blame the Separations, when we our ſelves maintain the firſt principles of ſetting up diſtinctions and ſeparations in the Church: But it is dangerous to be partiall in the lawes of Chriſt. Why may not the wofull neglect of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, viſible pledges of divine love; be one thing that makes miniſters be ſo contemptible and vile in the eyes of many as they are?</p>
            <p>Well, but to return, I ſay this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Sacrament is one of Chriſts commands, and he that breaks the leaſt of his commands, and teaches men ſo, ſhall be called the leaſt in the Kingdome of God. But I think Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath ſaid
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42522:25"/>enough to this to ſatisfie any ſober im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall Chriſtian, to whom I muſt ſtill referre the reader for further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on herein. The Doctor hath many quillets about this particular, which are more like to puzzle then to ſatisfie the reader. He ſtrives to put an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſure to ſome duties, as not common to all, and he inſtances in relations and ſex that come under the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſecond Table; the which duties are common and univerſall to all of the ſame relations and ſex. And what though it be not the duty of all Church members to preach and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Sacraments; yet it is the duty of all Miniſters what ever ſo to do. But Mr. <hi>H.</hi> argument is, If all other ſervice lie in common, it is an intrenchment upon the common liberty, to put an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſure upon the Sacraments. And if the Sacrament come under the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the firſt Table, as a part of Gods worſhip, it is equally binding to all, and ſo in common with the reſt of worſhip, notwithſtanding any thing yet made out to the contrary.</p>
            <p>It is true, affirmative precepts do not binde to every moment of time; but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42522:26"/>that will not juſtifie a careleſſe and wilfull neglect at any time. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is ſaid, that Church members are not bid abſolutely to come, but ſo to come, it ſeems ſtrange to me: I had thought that all precepts of worſhip had been abſolute to perſons of years, in the Church of Chriſt. And do this in remembrance of me is abſolute, and the principall duty, however the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor is pleaſed to call it carnall Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and a ſetting up the form above the power of worſhip. For in every duty there is a forme, which is heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to be obſerved; and it's impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble there ſhould be the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe without the form. To obey the voyce of God in regard of the matter injoyned, ſeems to be the main, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting reaſonable man: and when there is an externall conformity to the commands of the Lord, ſuch are ſaid to walk in the waies of the Lord, failings in the manner there will ſtill be; both good and bad are under a neceſſity of failings and miſcarriages in every thing, which is to be imputed to the common frailty of man fallen But not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what God commands at all is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42522:26"/>voluntary rebellion, and that which the Scriptures moſt uſually threaten ſevere judgements unto. But I hope the Doctor doth not mean that the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of the Lords Supper is the form, and ſelf-examination the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; which yet he ſeems to do by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions againſt making receiving to be the principal, the other but an acceſſary.</p>
            <p>To which exceptions, I ſay, Firſt, that this duty of examination of our ſelves is a private duty, and the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate is ſubordinate to the publick. Secondly, This duty was preſcribed oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally, as a remedy to that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar caſe of making a breach upon the materials of divine inſtitution and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and therefore a means to further them in the right obſervance of the Supper: and we may moſt ſafely ſay, the end is moſt principall, the means leſſe. Beſides, where the duty ceaſeth in ſome reſpects, it is not to be urged in thoſe reſpects; but it's clear there is not the ſame reaſon, for point of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as there was at <hi>Corinth,</hi> about the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacrament; the work of our congregations demeaning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42522:27"/>more reverently and orderly in a way ſutable to the carrying on of that ſervice in regard of the externall part, according to the rule of inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And therefore that duty is not to be urged upon ours with the ſame neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of danger of eating and drinking unworthily, as to the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.</hi> It is true, their ignorance, and not diſcerning of the Lords body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by the inſtituted ſigns, was the cauſe of all their other miſcarriages.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Doth it not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, that the ignorant amongſt us do neceſſarily run upon the ſame danger of miſcarriage?</p>
            <p>I anſwer,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
               </label> we know they do not: for ours many of them rather erre on the other hand, by putting too much holineſſe in the conſecrated elements, then by uſing them as common things: ſuch hath been the education of the moſt every where, that they conceive this Sacrament to be a moſt holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, appointed for the good of their ſouls. And therefore out of fear and reverence they do demean themſelves orderly, and regularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42522:27"/>to the externals of the inſtitution. Had the <hi>Corinthians</hi> come up to that conformity of Sacramentall actions, and order that ours generally do, we ſhould not have read of their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for unworthy receiving (as I humbly conceive) nor of their being urged ſo to come: for that principall duty is not to be neglected, though through careleſneſſe the other be.</p>
            <p>But then (ſaith the Doctor) <hi>It is a ſen to diſſwade men from doing their duty,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> be they never ſo vile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
               </label> the Doctor knowes there be other waies to reform ſuch enormities. He inſtances in perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to forbear duties of homage and worſhip; but not only Mr. <hi>H.</hi> but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſober Chriſtians, Miniſters, and others, judge that all the viſible ſubjects of Chriſts Kingdome, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obligation of his commands? And do this in remembrance of me, is one not to be reſtrained to ſex, ſuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or any particular relations; but to be obſerved in common by all the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized of years under Church indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. And if the Doctor hath any thing further to ſay, that may give ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42522:28"/>in that point, my ſelf and others will be very thankfull.</p>
            <p n="9">9. And ſo I come to the laſt Querie propounded; namely, whether there be any thing in the nature, language, actions or end of the Sacrament, in that place of the <hi>Corinths,</hi> or elſewhere, incongruous to the actuall receiving of the unregenerate in the Church.</p>
            <p>Before I come to anſwer directly to the Querie, I ſhall lay down theſe ſix propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I conceive that Sacraments in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and this in particular were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted for the ſpirituall good of the viſible Church of Chriſt comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively taken, in which every particular member is included.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the viſible Church of Chriſt conſiſts of perſons regenerate and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, profeſſing the true religion, and their ſeed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the unregenerate in the Church are the only proper and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate objects of the moſt ſundamentall promiſes in the Goſpell Covenant, of the giving the firſt grace.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the whole adminiſtration of the Covenant belongs to thoſe in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42522:28"/>Church, that are the immediate objects of the abſolute promiſes in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; they being of years of diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to uſe the ſame, in order to the Lords putting the promiſes into exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and performance.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That whom the promiſes of grace do reſpect, to them the uſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments do belong; Sacraments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing viſible repreſentations of the death and bloud of Chriſt, on which thoſe promiſes of grace are founded, and by which they are confirmed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That thoſe in the Church and of years, whom we cannot exclude from covenant relation, we may not exclude from the Sacraments, they being viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeales and pledges of Covenant love to that people that are in poſſeſſion of Covenant adminiſtrations, of divine Ordinances, of worſhip, as ours are.</p>
            <p>Theſe being truths (as I conceive they all are) I think it will follow, that there is nothing in the Word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the receiving of the unregenerate in the Church, being of years of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and profeſſing the true Religion</p>
            <p>The Doctor hath written very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandingly and informingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42522:29"/>the Covenant, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how it is ſealed; and yet he fals off in his concluſions and applications, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the unregenerate in the Church from the Sacramentall ſeals, whom yet he allowes to be objects of Covenant grace, ſaying that only the elect and perſons effectually called are the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and yet he intimates that the elect unregenerate are the object of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall grace; and that grace and faith be a part of the Covenant ſealed by the Sacrament: and yet he would not have thoſe receive that have not this faith and grace, though promiſed in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and ſealed in the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>But if the elect before converſion be in the writing, and in the Church, then Sacraments ſeal to them: but doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God hath his elect to call in the Church, elſe we cannot tell where they are; if not under the ordinary means of their calling. And therefore there can be no danger in ſealing that part of the Covenant to ſuch. And doth not the Doctor himſelf and others act ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly in adminiſtring the ſeal in Baptiſme? Are they within the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant then by vertue of a viſible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42522:29"/>in their parents, and upon that account ſealed with the Sacrament of Baptiſme; and yet grown to years de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the ſame ſeal of the Supper? If they had right then; how comes it to paſſe they have none now? The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſaith, <hi>Becauſe of their antifederall wickedneſſe, they prejudice themſelves, and deprive themſelves of covenant right: and that thoſe that are in the ſtate of nature, are out of the Covenant, and the groſly ignorant are ſuch, &amp;c. And therefore to be denied the ſacramentall Seal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, It's hard to ſuch, that any born in the Church of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Parents, they continuing to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold an externall profeſſion of the true Religion, are out of the Covenant, how ignorant or wicked ſo ever they be. For if there be a more immediate object of thoſe promiſes of giving the firſt grace, in the Church, where the ordinary means of working that grace are, then perſons in the ſtate of nature, and unregenerate in the Church are the immediate object of thoſe promiſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others out of the Church. But there is a preſent and immediate object of thoſe promiſes in the Church, that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42522:30"/>are under covenant ordinances; except the day of Gods giving the firſt grace be paſt in the Church. Therefore thoſe in the State of nature and unregenerate in the Church, are the preſent and moſt immediate object of thoſe promiſes in the Covenant of Gods giving the firſt grace. As for thoſe in the Church that have the firſt grace already, they cannot be the proper objects of it in the promiſe: and thoſe that are out of the Church, not having the ordinary means of putting thoſe promiſes into performance, cannot be the preſent and moſt immediate, or moſt likely objects.</p>
            <p>For as touching the ſtate of Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, the Apoſtle intimates plainly, <hi>That they are ſtrangers from the Covenants of promiſe, without hope, and without God in the world,</hi> Epheſ. 2.12. Therefore the unregenerate in the Church, are the preſent and moſt proper objects of thoſe promiſes, and conſequently of Sacraments that ſeal to the truth of thoſe promiſes. And for thoſe that will not allow men in the ſtate of nature and unregenerate, to be of the Church, they will allow the Covenant a full ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in the Church. And for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42522:30"/>ſins and perſonall miſcarriages in the Church, we are to make no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the regenerate and unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, there being the ſame rule to guide us in dealing with both. But let none miſtake me, when I ſay the unregenerate in the Church are the immediate and proper objects of the promiſes of the firſt grace, I do not mean that all ſuch in the Church muſt neceſſarily have that grace given them; but ſuch there are in the viſible Church, which by nature are as bad as any others, and in no conſideration dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the worſt of men conſidered in themſelves; but are ſimple ſinners wholly loſt with the reſt of fallen mankinde: That which makes the difference is out of themſelves; it's the meer good will and pleaſure of him that worketh all things after the counſell of his own will; giving grace to whom he will, of thoſe that in all reſpects are equall in ſin and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. So that when we ſhall come to judge of perſons in the Church, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the moſt evident characters of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regeneracy; yet we may not exclude them from being objects of covenant
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42522:31"/>grace and mercy; nor from the ſeals and pledges of that grace and mercy, during their abode in the Church, and the Churches indulgence toward them. In a word, nothing excludes from co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant relation, but the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt (which I fear many of our blaſphemous Sectaries are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of) and poſitive unbelief, ſuch as was in the hardned and obſtinate Jewes; who denyed the holy One, and true Meſſiah ſent among them; obſtinacy and Apoſtaſie in the juſtly excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, renouncing the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, hating to be reformed by the Churches cenſures; theſe things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, and nothing elſe. And this might ſuffice for anſwer to the Querie, but I ſhall adde two or three arguments more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The very nature of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Supper is a viſible Goſpell, repreſenting Chriſt crucified to ſight and all the other ſenſes, by inſtituted ſigns, which more ordinarily is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to the ear by the word: but in this all the ſenſes are made the inlets to the ſoul, carrying the knowledge of Chriſt crucified to the underſtanding
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42522:31"/>heart and conſcience. And I think the unregenerate in the Church, have as much need of being taught Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, by the viſible ſigns, as any others: and they have as much need of the benefit and advantage of their outward ſenſes, as the regenerate, and more, they being more dull and ſlow of ſpirit to underſtand or to be affected with the meaning and end of this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice then they are.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The main end of this ſervice, is to keep a continuall freſh remembrance of the death of Chriſt, and that ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction made by him; by which all the ſame bleſſings of the Covenant are procured to fallen man: Chriſts bloud was ſhed for many, for remiſſion of ſins; that he might gather into one the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, ſcattered abroad in all the world, and in all ages of the world, is the end of his death, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.52. And the Sacrament is to be obſerved in remembrance of that by all thoſe that profeſſe hope of being ſaved through the merits of his death; which the unregenerate in the Church do, and cannot be excluded from the number of thoſe many Chriſt ſhed his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42522:32"/>bloud for: and therefore it is proper for ſuch to remember the death of Chriſt, in order to their ſpiritual good, whom we cannot exclude from being the ſheep he died for.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The actions of taking, eating and drinking are naturall actions of the body, in reference to thoſe ſpirituall ends the inſtitution directs us to, the which actions the unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate are in a naturall and rationall capacity to performe externally as the Word requires. Though the Doctor be pleaſed to judge them altogether uncapable, as not having a hand to take, he making faith the hand, which he ſaith they have not; which indeed is true of the unregenerate: but is he able to prove, that by the act of taking and eating expreſt in the inſtitution is meant the act of faith? I rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it one thing among many others he takes for granted, which would give better ſatisfaction, to hear ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved by the Word, then to leave us meerly to credit the dictates of men.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The language of Sacraments runs in generall and indefinit termes, This
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42522:32"/>cup is the New Teſtament in my bloud, ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſins, drink ye all of it; ſo ſaith <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark;</hi> indeed <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the word <hi>many,</hi> to <hi>you,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a part of that many in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of charity; and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> judges of the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doubt not but if the Doctor exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the inſtitution well, he may finde enough to warrant a forbearance of that particular application in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of the Sacrament, which he ſo much urges in his Book. I cannot finde in Scripture language any ſuch thing as he makes giving and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to be.
<note place="margin">Pag 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> What danger is there of confirming the unregenerate in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, if they take and cat in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Chriſts death? Who have more need of remembring the death of Chriſt, then they that muſt periſh for ever, dying without the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving benefits thereof? Who have more need of thoſe gracious tenders of life &amp; favour, then ſuch in the Church? For is not regenerating grace a benefit that comes by the death of Chriſt? And is not remiſſion of ſins a benefit that comes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42522:33"/>by the death of Chriſt? And is not Chriſt and all his benefits exhibited by thoſe outward ſigns? And doth not that include or ſuppoſe a proper ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of thoſe benefits preſent; which the unregenerate and unpardoned in the Church are? What incongruity is there in all this? Beſides, it ſounds ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry harſh in the Church, to exclude this ordinance of Chriſt from being a renewing and a converting ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or a means of renewing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting grace to the unregenerate, they being the moſt proper objects of that grace, as it is held forth in the promiſes, for the putting of which into executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all the ordinances ſeem to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient.</p>
            <p>Again, that one main end of the work of the Miniſtry is the converſion of ſouls, none will deny; and I think none can exempt any eſſentiall part of that work from being a means ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to this end; and if no eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall part can be exempted, then not this of adminiſtring this Sacrament of the Supper, which none can deny to be an eſſentiall or neceſſary part of the Miniſters work in reference to the good
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42522:33"/>of ſouls. That ordinance in the Church that was inſtituted to ſhew forth the death of Chriſt till he come, is a means of converſion. But the Sacrament is an ordinance in the Church inſtituted to ſhew forth the death of Chriſt till he come. Therefore the Sacrament is a means of converſion. What may more ſtrongly move a ſinner to convert then the death of Chriſt, which ſets forth the hainouſneſſe of ſin, the wretched condition of the ſinner in himſelf, without Chriſt, and yet a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of ſalvation by Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The word and prayer (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly means of converſion) are ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the right adminiſtration of the inſtituted ſigns, that without them there is no Sacrament; and therefore to deny the Sacrament to be a means of converſion, is to deny the Word and Prayer to be a means of converſion; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we ſhall ſay that the adding of the inſtituted ſigns to the Word and Prayer hinders the power and efficacy of them from their intended end; ſo that though the Word and Prayer be means of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion out of the adminiſtration of the Sacrament, yet in it they are not.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Doctor ſaith, <hi>There
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42522:34"/>is no promiſe made to that Ordinance, in that reſpect:</hi> it is eaſily anſwered: for there is a promiſe of Chriſts preſence in every ordinance, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. Beſides, Precepts and Promiſes are relatives; in Precepts we are to underſtand Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes included, and in Promiſes Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts are underſtood. As ſinners are to ſeek God while he may be found, and to call upon him while he is neer; ſo they muſt ſeek him where he will be found. As we may not exclude the mercifull preſence of Chriſt from the Sacrament; ſo neither may we exclude ſinners in the Church from ſeeking Chriſt there. We know not but that a wilfull or careleſſe neglect of this one duty of worſhip and homage, may hinder a bleſſing from all the reſt: as he that turns his ear from the Law, his prayer ſhall be abominable.</p>
            <p>But when the Doctor cannot with any clearneſſe anſwer the argument to ſatisfaction, he would evade it, by allowing all preſence at the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration which he ſaith is profitable, and anſwers the end pleaded for, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And indeed in that his device Church members of years are beholding to him for his charity in allowing them
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42522:34"/>as much priviledge in order to the Sacrament, as he allowes to infidels, and the excommunicated.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If that bare preſence anſwer that end, then much more actuall recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, having the advantage of more of their bodily ſenſes, then meerly to be ſpectators: and I think that in yeelding this he hath granted the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and his putting the queſtion to actuall receiving, is not to any purpoſe; becauſe the act of receiving abſtracted from word and prayer, neceſſary eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentials to the very being of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, is but a civill thing only: And therefore the whole muſt goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to make up that ſervice; and his queſtion is beſide the queſtion. It is ſufficient to prove the argument, that the whole adminiſtration be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to that end; as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſtates the queſtion. But what devices do men finde out in pretence of advancing Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments? Some exclude all Infants, others ſome Infants in the Church. The papiſts will give the Sacrament but in one kinde; many among us in neither kinde. The Doctor will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low all preſence at the Sacrament:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42522:35"/>they may hear and ſee, but they may not taſte; they may not take and eat according to the Commandement.</p>
            <p>But why will he allow all to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent? <hi>Why, becauſe preſence may convert, but actuall receiving not, becauſe naturall men being preſent, may get good without that ſinne which they are in danger of by unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiving; but by their receiving they can receive no benefit; but do prejudice them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by their unworthy receiving, beſides their being guilty of murdering Chriſt. And ſhall we think, that that act, wherein they eat and drink judgement to themſelves, ſhall be ſo bleſſed of God, as to become a means of converſion to them, &amp;c. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, becauſe the committing of ſome groſſe and ſcandalous ſinne, is made by God an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of converſion; ſhall any take warrant therefrom to commit ſcandalous ſins, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all which I anſwer, That all which he hath to that purpoſe is ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued from meer miſtakes, he taking for granted all along, that the unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate in the Church, do neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eat and drink unworthily in the Apoſtles ſenſe; whereas I conceive the contrary hath been already fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. And therefore it would be well,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42522:35"/>if he would ſee his miſtake, and alter his judgement, that others might not be in danger of being miſled by him. In the mean time what he hath char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Mr. <hi>H.</hi> with in point of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication untruly, may be retorted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf juſtly, <hi>It is a cruell aſſertion, a bloudy tenent, &amp;c.</hi> And that not only in his depriving many ſouls of the benefit and ſpirituall good of ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed an ordinance; but in his detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting alſo from the goodneſſe, grace and power of God in that ordinance; as if Chriſt had appointed it in the Church, rather for the hurt, then for the ſpirituall good of his viſible ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, they partaking thereof conformly according to their preſent capacity.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But then (ſaith the Doctor) <hi>If it be a convering ordinance, we may adminiſter the Sacrament to the Heathen to convert them to Chriſtianity; for if it will convert thoſe in the Church that have but the form, to the power of Religion, then it will ſure convert the Heathen (at leaſt) to the form: if it will do the greater, much more the leſſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
               </label> That an argument drawn from the greater to the leſſer,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42522:36"/>muſt be of things of the ſame kinde, and ſo of men under an equall capacity, elſe it will not hold. I can throw a ſtone over a houſe, can I therefore throw a feather: this is leſſe then the other, and yet though the ſame arme and ſtrength be put forth, it will not do it. The fallacy of the argument lies in this, That there is not the ſame ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of receiving good by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in both: the formall profeſſing Chriſtian is not in ſuch an incapacity of receiving good by that ordinance as the Heathen are? We know that to Heathens, that never heard of Chriſt, or at leaſt do not acknowledge him their redeeming Lord, ſo as to come under his Lawes, no not ſo much as Baptiſme, the outward elements are but meer civill things. And they might be eaſily perſwaded to take and eat of thoſe elements of Bread and Wine, in order to the good of their bodies, but not for the good of their ſouls, before they own Chriſt to be their Lord, Redeemer and Saviour; till then they know not what theſe things mean. But thoſe among us, educated in the true Religion, do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42522:36"/>Chriſt their redeeming Lord; and they do know in ſome meaſure what theſe things of God mean: ſo that the Sacrament in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way, may work ſome proper effect upon the one, but can have none upon the other without a miracle. Beſides, it is clear enough, that as no uncircumciſed perſons were to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sanctuary, or to eat of the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over; ſo no unbaptized perſon is to partake of the holy Supper in that Communion. Were there the like ground of denying the Sacrament to the ignorant and ſcandalous perſons under Church indulgence, that there is of denying it to infidels; this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie had been at an end before this time. It cannot be denyed, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication is appointed in the Church, to convert and reduce the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate and wilful ſinners therein: doth it therefore follow, that we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe this means of converſion to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens out of the Church? What can be more abſurd? Nay, what have we to do to judge them that are without? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. The Doctor knowes well enough, that different premiſes will
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42522:37"/>not bear the ſame concluſions: and the truth is, for want of making pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes equall, according to Scripture preſidents, we have run upon falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions: to inſtance in ſome.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe we finde in Scripture the diſtinction of beleever and unbeleever, uſed to diſtinguiſh the Church from the World, how commonly is the ſame uſed to make a diſtinction in the Church amongſt us who in Scripture ſenſe are all beleevers: for it is evident, that an unbeleever? in the Scripture ſenſe, is either a Pagan infidell, or an unbeleeving Jew that abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces Chriſt, under the notion of a falſe Chriſt, a deceiver, a devill, &amp;c. refuſing to obey his Lawes, or to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſalvation by him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe we finde that theſe unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers are under wrath, <hi>Aliens from the common-wealth of Iſrael, ſtrangers to the Covenants of promiſe, without hope, and without God in the world. Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. Which was true of the <hi>Epheſians</hi> before they received the Goſpell; that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the unregenerate in the Church, are under the ſame condition, though they beleeve in a true ſenſe (though
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42522:37"/>not ſincerely) and are under the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and perſons to whom the adoption, and the giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God pertains, as once to the Jewes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4, 34. fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding warrant in the word to ſeparate from the Infidell and idolatrous world (eſpecially in matter of worſhip) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they conclude, we muſt ſeparate our ſelves from the unregenerate in the Church.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe we finde, that ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers have by their unworthy and undecent behaviour, in time of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, profaned the Sacrament to their own perill and judgement; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we conclude, Firſt, That thoſe whoſe perſons are unworthy (as not being regenerate) eat and drink un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily. Secondly, That ſome other unworthy actions of Chriſtians com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted before their comming to the Sacrament, renders them uncapable of worthy receiving; and conſequently renders them liable to judgement therein.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe we finde in the Scripture, ſome excommunicated for foul and ſcandalous ſins, and blaſphemous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:42522:38"/>therefore we conclude we may exerciſe Church cenſures for any ſin, even for omiſſion of ſuch duties as are dubious whether injoyned in the word or no; but I have done with theſe falſe concluſions.</p>
            <p>There is one objection more which the Doctor makes againſt Mr. <hi>H.</hi> Free Admiſſion; to which I deſire to ſpeak ſomething.</p>
            <p>The objection is this.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That Mr.</hi> H. <hi>Free Admiſſion ſtrengthens the hands of the wicked, by promiſing them lies in the Name of the Lord: and makes ſad the hearts of the righteous, whom God would not have made ſad, by their profaning the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp;c. And this he endevours to back with the language of the Sacrament, or words which the Miniſter uſes in the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of the Sacrament to particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: by his words and action, giving and tendring Chriſt and all his benefits of grace and glory to the wicked, as well as to the godly; the which grace and glory the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are appointed to aſſure and confirm, &amp;c. When as in the preaching of the word it is farre otherwiſe; the Miniſter therein not diſpenſing the ſame to all alike; but prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching comfort to whom comfort belongs,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42522:38"/>and terrour to whom terrour belongs, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall in anſwer to this objection,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
               </label> promiſe ſeverall things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Sacraments are of no other ſignification then what they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſignifie by the Word.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That what Sacraments ſignifie, that only they do neceſſarily teach, and nothing elſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the ſubject of Sacramentall teaching, or that which they chiefly teach, is Chriſt crucified, together with all the benefits that come thereby to the viſible Church, included in that particular bleſſing of remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the main end of the whole ſervice, is to bear in our mindes a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall remembrance of the death of Chriſt; the meriting and procuring cauſe of all grace and glory beſtowed upon baptized man.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the Adminiſtration of the Sacrament, is appointed in the Church as well to be a means of grace, as a pledge to aſſure thereof.</p>
            <p>To all this adde what hath been ſaid before concerning the unregenerate, in order to the Sacrament; and then make
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42522:39"/>it out he that can, that the language or adminiſtration of the Sacrament, to the wicked or unregenerate, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Church, doth ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked more then the Word may do; or promiſe them lies in the name of the Lord. I grant that falſe concluſions and applications may be drawn from the trueſt premiſes in the Word: and ſo likewiſe from the uſe of the Sacrament, through miſtake of our ſelves: but it doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, that the Word or Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment promiſeth lies to the hearer or receiver; when through an ignorant deceitfull heart, they miſapply the Word or Sacrament. For there are generall truths held forth indefinitely to all in both, though all do not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply the ſame. And the very ſame that is ſaid of the Sacrament, may be truly ſaid of the Word, as to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in hand, when rightly diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to men in the Church.</p>
            <p>Is not this the great, and moſt true aſſertion of the Goſpell, worthy to be received of all men, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. <hi>And alſo to ſeek and to ſave that which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42522:39"/>is loſt, to call to repentance, to juſtifie the ungodly, and to die for enemies,</hi> who yet in other places are called <hi>ſheep, his Church and friends,</hi> according to Gods electing love and gracious purpoſe? And is not this Goſpell to be preached to every creature, in order to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and effecting theſe ends of grace and ſalvation in ſuch as are ſinners ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, and loſt in themſelves, and ſimply ungodly? And dare any ſay, this is to promiſe lies to the ungodly and ſinners in the Church, and ſo to ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, that they may not return from their wickedneſſe? And what is the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given and received, but a viſible repreſentation of the death of Chriſt, and ſatisfaction made by him for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to put us in remembrance of all this; and which opens a door of hope to all in generall, and a peculiar comfort to them that can from their experience of grace received (with <hi>Paul</hi>) apply this to themſelves: <hi>Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners, whereof I am chief.</hi> I know what is uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put in againſt this generall aſſertion of the Goſpell, limiting the ſame to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42522:40"/>penitent ſinners, ſenſible of their being loſt, and of being enemies, &amp;c. But doubtleſſe out of ſome miſtake; and ſuch as doth reflect ſomewhat upon the publick Miniſtery (to which I would not be any way in the leaſt degree inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious) but becauſe ſuch like quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Mr. <hi>H.</hi> are excepted againſt by the reverend Doctor; I ſhall crave leave to expreſſe ſome of my thoughts in vindication of him.</p>
            <p>The Doctor ſaith, <hi>Chriſt came not to call the righteous, that is, ſuch as think themſelves ſo, but ſinners to repentance, that is, ſaith he, ſuch ſinners that are ſenſible of their ſinfulneſſe, ſick and loſt, &amp;c.</hi> But will not this then follow, that all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men, dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, thinking themſelves righteous, whole, and in the right way, and that they have need of nothing (with the <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceans</hi>) not knowing that they are wretched and miſerable, poor, and blinde, and naked, are out of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Chriſt came to call; and ſo by conſequence he came to call none at all; becauſe all by nature are ſinners under the forementioned Characters and black qualification of inſenſibleneſſe of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42522:40"/>ſin and miſery, and high thoughts of themſelves. And therefore the Doctors ſenſe is not like to be the true ſenſe and meaning. For we know what coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell Chriſt gives to the <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> who were ſuch conceited ſenſleſſe ſinners, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18. And how that he gives life to <hi>quicken them that are dead in ſins and treſpaſſes,</hi> Epheſ. 2.1. <hi>And is ſent to give repentance to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael, and remiſſion of ſins,</hi> Act. 5.31. For to ſay he gives repentance to the penitent, and life to the living, (as he doth if the Doctors ſenſe be right) is not the ſenſe of the Goſpell, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a truth in its proper ſenſe, without the advancing of the power of nature too high. And therefore ſuch ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conditions or qualifications are not required to put perſons into a capacity of receiving the benefits of the Goſpell Covenant: it being the ſupernatural be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and bleſſings of the Covenant that make any to be ſuch. It's true, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall grace precedes glory; and the firſt grace precedes the growth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe therein: but it is naturall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravity, ſinfulneſſe and miſcry that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily precedes the firſt ſaving grace; ſo that that cannot be a condition of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42522:41"/>the firſt grace, that is either the firſt grace it ſelf, or growth therein. The Covenant in this caſe is abſolute and inconditionall: but then I conceive the Covenant to be conditionall in other reſpects, in an eaſie and favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſenſe thus. The tenour of the Goſpell, to people that never yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced nor owned the Doctrine and ordinances of the Goſpell, runs thus, <hi>He that beleeves ſhall be ſaved; but the wrath of God abides upon thoſe nations, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and perſons, that either have not the Goſpell in the tender of it, or being tendred receive it not.</hi> But thoſe that upon the tender receive the Goſpell, ſo as to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit the truth thereof, and willingly come under the lawes and worſhip in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, forſaking all falſe religions, and joyn with the profeſſors of the true, ſuch are reckoned for beleevers, and come under the promiſes of grace and glory upon that account. And therefore the Apoſtle ſends ſalutations to <hi>all that in every place call upon the name of the Lord, both theirs and ours;</hi> and he applies that of the Prophet in this caſe, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall call on the Name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaved,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.2. Rom.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42522:41"/>10.13. That is, ſuch people are under the promiſes of ſalvation, in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thoſe that call not upon the Name of Chriſt Jeſus the Lord at all; as Jer. 10.25. <hi>Pour out thy fury upon the Heathen that know thee not, and upon the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies that call not on thy Name.</hi> I look upon belief of the truth as the only means of ingraffing the unbeleeving Jew or Gentile into the true Olive or viſible Church of Chriſt, out of which is no ſalvation; becauſe they have not the ordinary means of attaining the ſame. And where the means is, the Word profits not, when it is not mixt with faith in them that hear it. The Jew beleeved not the truth of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell at all: And he that comes to God muſt beleeve in the firſt place,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> 
               <hi>that God is, and</hi> then, <hi>that he is a bountifull rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that leads me to the next thing, namely, to conceive of all thoſe that are in externall convenant with God, in regard of their being in poſſeſſion of the Divine oracles and ordinances, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and promiſes, that all ſuch are under all the commands of Jeſus Chriſt: and the obſervance of thoſe commands
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42522:42"/>ſeems to me to be the condition of the Goſpell, and the grace thereof to be attained unto in the uſe of inſtituted means, and wayes appointed by Jeſus Chriſt in order to that end. And I do alſo conceive that not only half promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and it may bees, but whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſeem to reſpect perſons in the Church, doing but the morall, reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and externall duties. <hi>Aske and ye ſhall receive, knock and it ſhall be opened unto you, ſeek and ye ſhall finde. If you that are evill know how to give good things to your children, much more will your heavenly Father give the Spirit to them that aske it,</hi> even to them that have it not? <hi>Hear ye deaf, and ſee ye blinde, that ye may ſee.</hi> Iſa. 42.18. And again, <hi>hear and thy ſoul ſhall live.</hi> Iſa. 55.3. <hi>Ceaſe to do evill, learn to do well; and then come and let us reaſon together; though your ſins be as ſcarlet, they ſhall be white as ſnow; though they be red like crimſon, they ſhall be as wool.</hi> Iſa. 1.16, 17, 18. And after the Lord was pleaſed to expreſs the greateſt freeneſs of his grace to the houſe of Iſrael, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to give to them a new heart, and to put his ſpirit in them, and to make them his people, he addes, <hi>yet will I be required of for this by the houſe of Iſrael to do
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42522:42"/>it for them,</hi> Ezek. 36, 26, 27, 28, 37.</p>
            <p>And as the Lord hath made many promiſes to the uſe of means, ſo the uſe of means is ordinarily ſucceſſefull and bleſſed to attainment of grace. I do not ſay, that any by the uſe of means deſerve grace, or that God is bound to give grace to all uſe of means, or that he gives grace to any for the uſe of means and reaſonable ſerving of God. The bleſſing of grace is promiſed and alſo given freely according to the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Gods own will. And both the means &amp; the bleſſing upon the means is a fruit of Chriſts purchaſe by his bloud.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of thoſe in whom the promiſes of the firſt grace are performed: they ought diligently to apply themſelves to the uſe of all good means, and walk in all holy waies of Chriſtian obedience, for further growth and increaſe therein. All men ſtand bound to imploy all their abilities, and to put forth themſelves in all reall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours to improve their talents, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of common or generall endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or more peculiar bleſſings of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall grace, according to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages and opportunities given them,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42522:43"/>and ſhall be accountable to their Lord for them: this is the tenour of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and thus man is bound to do, whether God give the bleſſing or no: duties belong to man, the iſſue is the Lords: man is bound to him, but he is free to do whatſoever he pleaſeth in heaven and in earth. And yet it's true alſo that the promiſes of eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and bleſſedneſſe, belong only to thoſe that are actually juſtified and ſanctified; and do patiently continue in weldoing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. And this I think is neither Antinomianiſm nor Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagianiſm; but the tenour and ſcope of the Covenant of grace to man. So then if we conſider men under ſin and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, being in the Church, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the commands of the Goſpel, which juſtifies their obſervance of thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, in hope of a bleſſing. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to promiſes in that particular caſe, the unworthy gueſſe in the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, was not ſentenced for his being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and without the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when he was commanded to come to the feaſt (for ſo were all that were bidden as well as he) but his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the Goſpell, and having li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42522:43"/>to ſit down, and eat of every diſh of that feaſt of fat things, and yet at the end of the feaſt, being found to be one not having a wedding garment; this was damning; and for this he was ſentenced to be bound hand and foot, and to be caſt into utter darkneſs, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.11, 12, 13. This is a place uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally miſapplyed: for it proves no more then this, That of thoſe that have the advantage of Goſpell admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, ſome may and do periſh, for not having the grace of the Goſpell. <hi>Many are called, but few are choſen.</hi> But this by the way; I will return to the other part of the objection made by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor againſt Mr. <hi>H.</hi> free admiſſion, which is this, namely, <hi>That it makes ſad the hearts of the godly, to ſee the ordinance profaned, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, Why ſhould the hearts of the godly be made ſad, becauſe unregenerate perſons join with them in duties of homage and worſhip, and are willing to join with them in the uſe of the Word and Prayer as well as the Sacrament, as means of a bleſſing? Why ſhould any be grieved that wicked
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42522:44"/>men and ſinners are objects of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, Covenant bleſſings and mercy? ſhall the eye of any be evill, becauſe God is good, in ſending Chriſt into the world to ſave ſinners? Should not all remember that they themſelves were ſuch, though now through free grace they be waſhed, and ſanctified and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Chriſtians that are partakers of this grace, are all this by vertue of Electing love, Redemption and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant grace. None of us by nature, were any better then our fellow ſinners. It was the meer good pleaſure of God in Chriſt, that hath made us to differ. And what have any that they have not received, and that in the uſe of the ſame ordinary means, you ſtomach at in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers your fellow ſinners? Where would you have ſinners to ſeek Chriſt Jeſus but in the Temple? Where ſhall they finde him, but where he is? Chriſt bids all that will come and take of the true bread and water of life freely, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. He doth no where diſcourage any from coming to him. O that Miniſters would rather woo ſinners, and ſeek by all fairneſſe and love to draw them to wait upon Chriſt in the way of all his
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:42522:44"/>ordinances, in order to bleſſing; then cauſleſly, upon miſtake, to diſcourage them, and take them off from endevou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after their duty of remembring the love of Chriſt, in his laying down his life for ſinners! but I muſt contract.</p>
            <p>But then ſaies the Doctor, <hi>If this be ſo,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> let all come pell-mell, and then where is the reformation ſo much indevoured after of late?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
               </label> That if by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all pell-mell, be meant all, though they come to mock at, or openly to abuſe the ordinance, I ſay it doth no way follow from what I have aſſerted, nor from any thing Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath ſaid. For he hath very well ſtated the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and excepted infants, diſtracted and juſtly excommunicated perſons; and theſe being excepted, if he or I ſay, let all come that will, I think it neither to be abſurd nor dangerous; ſeeing that Chriſt, when he offers himſelf, and the thing ſignified in the Sacrament, ſaith, <hi>Let him that is athirſt come; and whoſoever will, let him take the water of life freely,</hi> Rev. 22.17. Why may not we ſay of all of years, under Church indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence (whether Presbytered or not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42522:45"/>Presbytered) they offering themſelves to receive, are not to be denyed the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament for ſuppoſed incapacity or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe? Beſides, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath given a rationall account of his own practiſe, to acquit himſelf from ſuch reproachfull expreſſions, as are uſed againſt him, namely, That he hath done his utmoſt <hi>(de jure)</hi> that all come pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared: And that none may charge him with arrogance, he modeſtly and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly breaks out into this patheticall expreſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But woe is me, if I juſtifie my ſelf, who am a man of unclean lips, and dwell among people of unclean lips, eminent only in failings!</hi> By which words he doth not detract what he had ſaid before, but only ſhewes, that though ſuch were his frailty, that he (as all other) failed and came ſhort in every duty, yet he had not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglected or wholly omitted any duty in that reſpect, which Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of him. And ſo whether Mr. <hi>H.</hi> or the Doctor favours moſt of pride and vanity, let the intelligent and ſober judge.</p>
            <p>Now to the other part of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, namely, <hi>Where is the reformation
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42522:45"/>ſo long indevoured after, if we allow of ſuch a free admiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. I would learned men did more ſtudy by the right means, and in the right way to reform a true Church la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring under ſome corruptions in Doctrine, worſhip and diſcipline; which is our caſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I would fain know whether the debarring of Church members of years, and not excommunicated from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament be a means of reforming ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved in the Word.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether the want of diſcipline do juſtifie a totall neglect or ſuſpenſion of Sacraments, in order to reformation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether ſeparation in the Church be a good expedient to further the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the whole.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether to aboliſh the eſſentials of Church diſcipline, in the uſe thereof, for ſome exorbitant abuſes, be a good expedient to reform the thing.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether denying the Sacrament to thoſe whom the Church cannot juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceed againſt, the poſitive excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication be any furtherance to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:42522:46"/>
            <p n="7">7. Whether there can be any refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Church in that reſpect, untill diſcipline be reſtored, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formly exerciſed in the ſame; and if ſo, whether the Sacrament muſt be ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded till then, and whether it be any thing towards reformation ſo to doe.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether the very nature and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of reformation in the viſible Church, ſtands not only in the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conformity to the indiſputable Lawes of Chriſt their head; conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all to an uniformity thereunto. When theſe few queries are anſwered ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the reverend Doctor, or any other that holds the Church of <hi>England</hi> a true conſtituted Church, as to its eſſentials and being; if I live, and God enable me thereto, I may take occaſion to make a further and more direct anſwer to that latter part of the objection con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning reformation.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I ſhall go on to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate Mr. <hi>H.</hi> in what he aſſerts touching excommunication, and cenſures of the Church. For what he hath aſſerted concerning theſe, is by the Doctor charged to be <hi>falſe, bloudy tenants, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:42522:46"/>
            <p>And here I ſhal firſt aſſert what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive is truth, and then anſwer to what the Doctor hath ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I conceive that none are proper objects of excommunication, but ſuch as are in the true Church of God, and in fellowſhip with the Saints in all acts of communication and worſhip pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. <hi>For what have I to do to judge them that are without? them God judges,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That no one is to be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, but in caſe of violating ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and known Law of Chriſt: and that violation periſted in to obſtinacy; after a judiciall triall, conviction, and patient waiting of the Church, for his reformation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That none may exerciſe the key of Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline, but ſuch perſons in office to whom all the keys of Chriſts Kingdome are committed, being appointed by him to preach the Word and adminiſter the Sacraments as well as exerciſe diſcipline.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That no ſingle paſtour alone, but ſuch as are ſo in an aſſociation, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive authority from the whole, can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Church cenſures authoritatively;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42522:47"/>and that every Presbyter in generall is not to have a part in this power, but ſome in ſpeciall choſen by the whole Church, which are more eminently qualified and fitted for the exerciſe of Eccleſiaſticall rule and government.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That excommunication, when it is juſt, is a ſolemn ejecting or putting out of obſtinate ſinners in the Church, from all acts of communion and worſhip of God in the publick congregation; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till by repentance they manifeſt both their ſhame and ſorrow for their ſin; and upon the manifeſtation of this, and publick promiſe of amendment, the Church ought to be ſatisfied therewith; and the penitent offender to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and regularly admitted to all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Church priviledges again.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That thoſe have much to anſwer for, that were the occaſion of laying Gods vineyard waſte, by throwing down the wall, and plucking up the hedge of diſcipline eſtabliſhed, before they were agreed of another warranted by the Word, to be ſet up in ſtead thereof. By this time they may both ſee their folly and feel the ſmart of it in the evil effects and conſequences.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:42522:47"/>
            <p>Well, having laid down theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, let me a little apply them, and ſhew you what will follow upon the truth of them. And firſt, if the firſt be true (as I conceive it is) then thoſe that never were admitted to the Lords Supper, are not in a capacity of theſe cenſures of the Church; nor to be amended by them, what ever their enormities be. If the ſecond be true, then none in the Church may be cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for ignorance, or for the omitting of doubtfull duties; eſpecially that of ſubmitting to Church examination, in order to the Sacrament. If the third be true, then not only the common members, but the ruling Elders will be called in queſtion for uſurping the key of Diſcipline; they not having power to exerciſe the key of Doctrine and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. If the fourth be true, then we may take notice how little of true diſcipline is practiſed in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and in what an incapacity we are (for the preſent) of any true refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; whatever ſome pretend. But the ſixt and laſt I intend more eſpecially to clear up in vindication of Mr. <hi>H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And take it thus.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:42522:48"/>
            <p>Excommunication is a delivering to Satan for the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirit may be ſaved in the day of the Lord. It's a great thunder-bolt &amp; puniſhment inflicted by the Church, as the laſt remedy to reduce the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate from the way of periſhing <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> ſaith, As Chriſt is in the Church, ſo Satan is out of the Church; to which condition the excommunicated are ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced: but with a mercifull end; to reduce them to Chriſtian obedience, where God gives the bleſſing. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is the very beginning of hell, and eternall wrath; when the ſentence is juſt; it being confirmed in heaven. <hi>Put out from among you that wicked perſon,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.13. He muſt be put out from among themſelves, and ſo out of all communion. The ſame word ſeems to be <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.22. and 12.42. where it is ſaid of ſome, that they durſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt for fear of the Jews, for they had a greed, that if any did confeſſe him, they ſhould be put out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue. So that if the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in the cenſure of the inceſtuous perſon, have any reference to the practiſe of the Jewes, (as the Doctor ſeems to hint)
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:42522:48"/>why then doubtleſſe he was put out of the Churches aſſemblies. For it is moſt certain, the Synagogues were places of caſe, where the Jewes publiquely aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for divine worſhip, of prayer, reading, preaching, &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 13, 14, 15, 16. So that I ſay, if <hi>Paul</hi> followed the practiſe of the Jewes, or meant that the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſhould proceed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their practiſe in this; then his meaning was, that they ſhould put out that wicked perſon from their aſſemblies for communion and worſhip I profeſſe I cannot but wonder the Doctor ſhould be ſo tart with Mr. <hi>Humphrey</hi> in this thing; he having the very letter of the Text, and the practiſe of the Jewes Church to warrant what he hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in this point. For let me aske the reverend Doctor how he or any other of his opinion will reconcile that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering to Satan out of the Church, and allowing their preſence in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, in all acts of worſhip and ſpirituall communion, except actuall receiving of the Sacrament of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per? To put out that wicked perſon from among themſelves: and at the ſame time to allow him preſence among
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:42522:49"/>themſelves; and to have communion with them in all acts of worſhip except the Supper, are altogether inconſiſtent. Neither doth that any thing at all help, which the Doctor ſo often urges in his book; <hi>Let him be as a Heathen or publican: But Heathens and publicans may be preſent at all the ordinances,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.24. <hi>And therefore the excommunicate may; becauſe they are not to be unto the Church worſe then a Heathen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For to this I have many words to ſay, which I think will anſwer the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It will appear that ſcandalous brethren are in ſome reſpect worſe then infidels. <hi>If any provide not for his own, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for thoſe of his own houſe; he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the faith, and is worſe then an infidell,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.8. And it had been better for revolting Chriſtians, <hi>never to have known the way of righteouſneſſe,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.21. <hi>And there was not ſuch a thing ſo much as named among the Gentiles, that one ſhould have his fathers wife,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.1. And when ſcandalous brethren are worſe then Heathens, in ſinning under ſuch means of better obedience, that Heathens have not; there is reaſon they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:42522:49"/>ſomething of priviledge that Heathens may have.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's clear that ſcandalous brethren are to be denied that priviledge in civill commerce and familiarity that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens are allowed to have with Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Chriſtians with them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9, 10, 11. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.27. compared. Liberty is given to Chriſtians to have civill and friendly familiarity with infidels, and fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the world; which yet is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to be denyed to ſcandalous and diſorderly brethren; as a means to bring them to ſhame. And if ſcandalous brethren under triall or actuall cenſure, are to be debarred of ſome priviledge that heathens are allowed: it will ſomewhat weaken the ſtrength of the Doctors argument.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtles had direct and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commiſſion (after Chriſts aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) to preach unto the Heathen; and therefore had warrant to admit of their voluntary preſence to hear in any place where opportunity might give the advantage of converting them. But yet upon their rejecting the Goſpel when it was faithfully tendred to them;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:42522:50"/>the Apoſtles might ſhake off the duſt of their feet againſt them; and leave them deeper under wrath. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeving Jewes were within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion too; but when they rejected the words of eternall life, and abuſed the meſſengers of Chriſt, that preached this to them, it's ſaid, <hi>they judged themſelves unworthy of eternall life;</hi> and upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the Apoſtles forſake them. Moſt terrible things are written againſt the diſobedient to the Goſpell. And I am ſure, Chriſtians that reject the Lawes of Chriſt (as the excommunicated are ſuppoſed to do) are worſe then Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, that never had the means of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and doing what Chriſt commands. As in reſpect of ſin and eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thoſe that live under the Goſpell, but refuſe to ſubmit to it, may be ſaid to be worſe then Heathens; ſo why not in point of externall Church privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge likewiſe; they having forfeited all thoſe priviledges of word, prayer, Sacraments, ingaging all powerfull means of their reformation, which heathens never had the advantage of. And it is ſuppoſed that Chriſt is reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in all the ordinary means ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:42522:50"/>to reclaim the ſcandalous and obſtinate in the Church, before this ſentence of excommunication is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced and put in execution againſt them. And juſt it is, that they that obſtinately reject all, ſhould be baniſhed from all; that they may either return to their duty by repentance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by give ſatisfaction to the Church, and be again received into communion: or elſe adde to obſtinacy apoſtaſie; alſo be rejected for ever, that the Name of God be not evill ſpoken of, becauſe of ſuch ſcandalous members.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Let him be to thee as a Heathen or Publican:</hi> that is, let the excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted be as odious, and as abominable to thee as a Publican, or Roman officer ſitting at the receit of cuſtome, was to the Jewes: or as a Heathen was to the Jewes, during the preſent ſtate of the Jewiſh Church (with reſpect to which Chriſt ſpeaks) when the uncircumciſed were an abomination to the Jewes; they being forbidden to let any ſtranger or uncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed in the fleſh, come into Gods Sanctuary, or partake of any priviledge of worſhip, but upon being a Proſelyte. And let the excommunicated be as ſuch
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42522:51"/>a one, and then what hath the Doctor and his party gotten?</p>
            <p>Touching the practiſe of the Greek Churches urged: I ſay what is that to us, when it is not agreeable to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the firſt Apoſtolicall Church of Chriſt? For upon the like ground on which they made four degrees of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, they might have brought in ten. And therefore not ſo much their practiſe, as the ground thereof is to be regarded in this point.</p>
            <p>But then the Doctor addes, <hi>That if this admitting of the excommunicated to be preſent at all ordinances be an error, it is out of indulgence, and an errour on the right hand: for whereas he excludes from one or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, he might exclude from all, according to Mr. H. tenent,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To this I anſwer; right hand er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours are evill as well as left, and to be taken heed of; and therefore not to be pleaded for, but to be reformed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suſpenſion from the Sacrament only is no legall cenſure. 1. Becauſe it hath no ground nor footing in the Word. 2. Becauſe it is the ſame with excommunication, according to the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:42522:51"/>Doctors own principles and practiſe. For he allowes preſence at all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances in the Church in both; and his proceedings in order to both are the ſame. And he and the reſt of his opinion and way, not coming up to the true nature of Church cenſures, do as much as in them lies, hinder the end of cenſures; which is, that the perſons cenſured may either be aſhamed and penitent, and ſo return to Chriſtian obedience; or elſe renounce their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and turn Apoſtates. Thus I humbly conceive, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> tenent is no bloudy tenent; but a moſt mercifull way and means ſet up in the Church, and left to be uſed as the laſt remedy, for the cure of the moſt deſperate ſouls: And not to uſe this remedy according to its nature and true intent of Chriſt therein, is to deprive, the obſtinate of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor of the only means left of his amendment and ſalvation; and ſo is indeed far from being an errour on the right hand. And yet by the way, to expreſſe my thoughts a little further: I hold that all unneceſſarily friendly familiarity with ſcandalous diſorderly brethren, that ſin out of wilfulneſſe,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:42522:52"/>whether they be under Church indui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, triall, or cenſure, is to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined according to that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10, 11. which ſenſe I humbly conceive comes neerer the meaning of the place, then to underſtand it of, or to inferre therefrom a ſuſpenſion from the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing that I ſhall ſpeak to, is the Doctors exceptions againſt ſome of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> quotations of Scripture, concerning which I ſay; let him but allow Mr. <hi>H.</hi> the ſame liberty he takes himſelf in ſome of his own quotations, and then he will have little cauſe to finde fault for his impertinent allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Scripture. I have given ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſome of the Doctors already: I ſhall here take notice of two or three more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He urges many texts of Scripture to prove that ſome in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were debarred the priviledges of worſhip for morall uncleanneſſe: but his proofs in that fal ſhort of what they are brought to prove; being in caſes that will not ſerve his turn. For ſuch perſons in the Jewiſh Church, came under the cenſure of the Judicial Laws,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:42522:52"/>which were very ſevere againſt ſuch offenders: and there is nothing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in <hi>Moſes</hi> or the Prophets (that I know of) in reference to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. And in that Church, the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters charge concerning uncleanneſſe is to be underſtood of ceremoniall and Gentile uncleanneſſe.</p>
            <p>Again, for that <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. brought by the Doctor to prove that ſome in the Church not excommunicated were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean. I deny that thoſe the Apoſtle there ſpeaks of, were of the Chriſtian Church. Let him conſult with the tenth verſe, and he may eaſily ſee the Apoſtle means thoſe vain talkers and deceivers that were eſpecially of the circumciſion: they profeſſe they know God, (as other unbeleeving Jewes did) but in their works they deny him, being abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and diſobedient, and to every good work reprobate, verſ. 16. They were either ſuch as never were of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, or if they were once of it, yet now were revolted and become Apoſtates by their horrid opinions, and abominable impieties. And then what is this to members of a Chriſtian Church, profeſſing Chriſtianity?</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:42522:53"/>
            <p>Again, for Church examination in order to the Sacrament, the Doctor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Be ready alway to give an anſwer to every man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you, with meekneſſe and fear; having a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp;c.</hi> The ſcope of the place is to ſhew what a Chriſtians duty is when they are apprehended, and under the terrour of perſecuting adverſaries: which duty is to be ſo far from being affrighted from their Chriſtian profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; that in ſuch caſe, they ſhould be alwaies ready to give a reaſon of the hope that is in them with meekneſſe and fear, &amp;c. And the Apoſtle urges them to this duty of conſtancy from a great incouragement, <hi>If you ſuffer for righteouſneſſe ſake, happy are ye,</hi> verſ. 14. Now how impertinent is this place for Church examination, or examination by the Paſtour or Elders before admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the Sacrament. If ſuch kinde of proofs be ſufficient to warrant that practiſe of examination, and ſuſpenſion from the ordinance for neglect of it, men may prove any thing they have a minde to; and make every fancy of their own a neceſſary duty; and ſo make
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:42522:53"/>void the neceſſary Lawes of God by their traditions.</p>
            <p>I ſhal inſtance in one quotation more, and then I have done: and it is 2 Pet. 3.5. <hi>For this they are willingly ignorant of, that by the Word of God the heavens were of old, &amp;c.</hi> This the Doctor quotes to prove that groſſe ignorance in Church members is a ſcandalous ſin, for which the Church may proceed to cenſure them, and to ſuſpend them from the Sacrament: but ſure this is not very pertinent to his purpoſe, as will eaſily appear, if he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with the Context. This ſecond Epiſtle was written to ſtir up their pure mindes by way of remembrance, that they might be mindfull of the words ſpoken before by the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to arme them againſt thoſe Scoffers that ſhould come in the laſt daies: 2 Pet. 3.1, 2, 3. <hi>Knowing this firſt, that there ſhall come in the laſt daies ſcoffers, walking after their own luſts; and ſaying, Where is the promiſe of his coming,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Scoffers at the Promiſe;</hi> which notes the higheſt degree of defection from and renouncing of piety, ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1. of the three degrees of ungodly men the <hi>ſcoffers or ſcorners</hi> is the laſt, as being the worſt.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:42522:54"/>And by theſe are meant ſuch as fell off and joined their ſelves with the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Jewes, complying with them; and falling into all the villany in the world, expreſt here by walking after their own luſts, that is, going on habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually as in a conſtant courſe, doing whatſoever ſeemed right in their own eyes, without any reſtraint of law, of nature, of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the ſecond chapter of this ſecond Epiſtle, they are ſet forth in their colours; to be ſuch as had eſcaped the pollutions that are in the world, through the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and by apoſtaſie were intangled again therein, and overcome, and ſo their latter end was worſe then the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. They that have been converted from their heathen ſins, by receiving the knowledge and faith of Chriſt, and then again relapſe and turn to them again, this latter eſtate of theirs, this Chriſtian Heatheniſme is worſe then their bare Heatheniſme at firſt. They had knowledge enough to bring in damnable hereſies, and wicked looſe opinions; to wreſt the Scriptures, to trouble the Church, and unſettle many:
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:42522:54"/>but they were willingly ignorant of the Word of God; they had the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Scripture, but againſt their knowledge did pervert the ſame, and wreſt all the Scriptures to their own deſtruction; as the learned Papiſts and our Apoſtate Sects do. But what is this to the ſimple ignorant among us, that out of careleſneſſe meerly, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacity and weakneſſe are ſo; and yet adhere to the true religion by profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion amongſt us? Theſe are ſtrange miſtakes and applications of Scriptures: but I hope the Doctor is not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant. By this he may ſee how ſevere he is againſt that in Mr. <hi>H.</hi> which he is more guilty of himſelf. But I have done with this, intreating him and all others into whoſe hands this ſhall come, to make a charitable ſenſe and conſtruction of what I have here written, and not to be offended, or prejudiced at the plainneſſe of the matter or rudeneſſe of the expreſſions and method, becauſe I want thoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that ſhould help all this.</p>
            <p>The Lord knowes that I herein in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend plainneſſe, and ſo farr as I know my own heart, I have thus declared my
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:42522:55"/>judgement in theſe things in upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſincerity, hoping they may be a means of the Churches good, tending to her peace and unity; and I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded will be ſo if prejudice or ſome other thing do not hinder the ſerious conſideration, right underſtanding and uſe of what I have here written. And ſo I have done with the reverend Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</p>
            <p>And I ſhall now from the grounds and principles laid down in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going diſcourſe, crave leave to hint a few things to the diſſenting brethren of the Congregationall way: and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe if the Presbyterian way (as ſome do practiſe) will not hold and ſtand good, much leſſe will the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent novelty in point of ſeparation, and gathering Churches out of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian congregations or others, and therefore give me leave (you that are for that way) to ſpeak freely unto you in a few words.</p>
            <p>If you judge the Miniſtry and the ordinances and particular congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons lawfull as to the main, why do you ſeparate from them, and gather out their beſt members from them? would
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:42522:55"/>you be content to be ſo ſerved by other ſeparated Churches? Doth not this ſenſibly inſinuate to the world, that thoſe gathered Churches are the only Churches of Chriſt, and ſo all other congregations (not after your moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) thereby called into queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be Churches of Chriſt or no? Are you for order and edification, and for the peace of the whole, or are you not? Do you intend the reformation of the whole, or of a part only? If you be only for the reformation of a part, and your deſire be to draw up ſome to purity of ordinances and ſpirituall communion with Chriſt their head, and one with another, what muſt become of all the reſt that are not of your minde, nor indeed in a capacity of admittance unto you, upon your termes and qualifications of members? what will you make of them that are not ſo qualified? will you account them members of the true viſible Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, and yet not fit to be of particular congregations, and enjoy communion with Chriſt in all his holy ordinances?</p>
            <p>Are they by vertue of the holy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:42522:56"/>of grace, Church natives and members borne; and declared to be ſuch by publick teſtimony on the Churches part in adminiſtring of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme unto them, a great Church pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, of right belonging to none but ſuch as are in externall Covenant with God at leaſt, either by profeſſion of faith in themſelves, or by their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and yet not fit to be owned, or received into communion by any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular congregation? Why, what a caſe are we in then? Your ſelves were equall with the reſt in your Baptiſme, and under the ſame adminiſtration of worſhip and ſervice that others were: and if you have found a bleſſing in your regeneration and effectuall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, keeping in that ſtation, why doe you forſake it now? Hath the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, in the uſe of ordinary means, brought quickning grace and life to your ſouls (which is the main in order to eternall bleſſedneſſe) whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will you go to mend your ſelves? Why ſhould you be ſo offended at the preſence of ſuch as you your ſelves once were? Did ſuch kinde of perſons hinder the power and bleſſing of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:42522:56"/>from doing you good before, that you are ſo zealous in ſeparating from them now? Will not the effects of free grace which you have already received convince you, that it is good for you to keep your former ſtation, and wait upon the ſame God in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for increaſe and compleating of what he hath begun? What fault can you finde with Word, Sacraments and Prayer (the main eſſentials of holy worſhip) they being the ſame both with us and you? only you are grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that ſinners ſhould enjoy the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of all theſe, though you as bad as they have found good in the uſe of all theſe. Would you have Jeſus Chriſt ſave no more then thoſe that are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſaved, or in a ſaving ſtate? Would you have the effects of Covenant love, flowing from a bleeding Saviour unto ſinners now to ceaſe? Had not meer grace and mercy prevented when you were ſinners, you had been impenitent ſinners ſtill like to the worſt. Will not the remembrance of what you once were beget ſome bowels of tenderneſſe toward ſuch ſinners? Is this your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration the way to draw on others
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:42522:57"/>that are weak ones, and to recover of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending brethren? Is this the way to do their ſouls good, to rail and revile them with reproachfull ſpeeches and ſlanders, calling them the World in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Church, and unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, aliens, profane ones, dogs, and ſwine, and the like? Nay, is not this the way rather to caſt ſtumbling blocks before the blinde, and to deſtroy many weak brethren whom Chriſt hath died for, by hardning them in an evill way? Is it not a means to make them apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize from the true Religion, and turn Papiſts or any thing, to keep the name of Chriſtians, rather then to be under that reproach of Infidels, Heathens, the profane world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You would have them left to wander in their own waies, and ſo you make them objects of the threatnings, but not of the grace of the Goſpell and promiſes; under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, but not under the promiſes made to Goſpell adminiſtrations. I wonder at it, that ſuch Miniſters would be accounted the only men that patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize free grace, and the only Goſpell Preachers; and yet forget that Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:42522:57"/>and to give repentance and remiſſion of ſins; to ſeek and to ſave that which is loſt, as all were and are untill he finde them and gather them to himſelf by a bleſſing of ſpirit and power in the uſe of his own ordinances. The Scriptures di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh indeed between the Church and the World; but theſe men will be making a world in the Church, and a world out of the Church: and make Infidels of the baptized, and ſuch as were born in the Church, and make a profeſſion of faith, and that truly too an to the object at leaſt, and yeeld ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall conformity in the materials of worſhip and Chriſtian obedience. But you that are ſo bold to unchurch Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and to make ſpoile in Chriſts Kingdome; did you ever read any ſuch thing approved in the Scriptures? I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe theſe are bold times; but let not men make too bold with Jeſus Chriſts intereſt; ſuffer him to have his full poſſeſſions and dominion over all his ſubjects that profeſſe loyalty and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage unto him in the world. Let us wiſh grace and peace to all that call on the name of the Lord Jeſus both theirs and ours; and let us have uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:42522:58"/>with them and communion too in all the Lawes and ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt. He hath ſpirit and grace ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to anſwer all the wants, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all the evils of all that ſeek after him according to his own inſtitutes. Oh brethren hinder none in ſeeking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Jeſus: diſcourage none becauſe they are ſinners from coming under the moſt ingaging ordinances to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Chriſtian obedience; do not act ſo contrary to the Apoſtolicall daies. The Apoſtles did what they could to convert the world unto Chriſtiani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and rejoyced in bringing ſinners to the obedience of faith: and were all for the inlarging of Chriſts kingdome, for which end they put themſelves upon the greateſt hazards. And will many of you pervert Chriſtianity into the world,' Chriſt into <hi>Belial,</hi> unchurch and unchriſtian ſuch as the Apoſtles did generally imbrace, and receive to communion upon as ſlender grounds as ours are deſired to be received? Did you over read that they refuſed any one that imbraced the Doctrine of faith, and was willing to be baptized? Did you ever read that they required
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:42522:58"/>more to breaking of bread, then they did to Baptiſme? Did you ever read, that they called any in the Church Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleevers, Heathens, Belial, Dogs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Did you ever read of this diſtinction of Church and World in any of thoſe Churches the Scriptures ſpeak of? I would you would prove a twofold world, one in the Church, another out of the Church: and a twofold King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the viſible Church of Chriſt, where men and women generally ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Lawes and Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt. Will you confound things that ſo much concern the Lord Chriſts intereſt? can you put no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the unregenerate under Covenant lations and adminiſtrations, and the infidel world that are left to wander from all theſe, and to ſacrifice to the Devill, and not unto the true God at all? Will you allow them no better ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and priviledges then you will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to Heathens? I wonder what rule you walk by, and judge by, and what ſpirit it is that you act ſo vigorouſly from. Suppoſe the <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>America</hi> ſhould generally embrace the Chriſtian faith, and diſavow their worſhipping
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:42522:59"/>of Devils, and deſire to imbody them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with thoſe that profeſſe the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, would you not offer them Baptiſme, and upon their coming under it, would you not admit them to all the ordinances of Chriſtian profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and communion? Whether you would or no, the Apoſtles have done it in the like caſe. Or ſuppoſe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell Jewes ſhould be convinced of their miſtake, and ſhould now confeſſe that Jeſus whom their fathers crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is the true Meſſiah and Saviour of the world; and upon that account re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their errour, and deſire the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of Chriſt, profeſſing their reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſubmit unto his adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and come under Chriſtian obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, would you refuſe them and not baptize them untill they were ſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified as to come up to your termes of communion? I think you would not. And I pray then, why will you ſeparate from the moſt of ours that are lawfully baptized, and come up to the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and are of no other religion but the Chriſtian religion, and expect ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by Chriſt alone? Is it becauſe they have this by education and the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:42522:59"/>helps of tradition, which in the other caſe is not ſo? I pray you do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue any benefits and helps that are the conſequences of the Covenant of grace. Remember how ſadly the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle laid it to heart, when the Jewes by their infidelity in denying Chriſt to be the Son of God, did unchurch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and apoſtatize, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.1. and the 11. compared. It was not their being carnall and otherwiſe ignorant and wicked, but their not beleeving that Chriſt was the Meſſias promiſed unto their fathers, that did unchurch them and their poſterity to this day: for that unbelief was the thing that barr'd them from his adminiſtrations, &amp; ſo are ſaid to be cut off, although by birth pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge they were the only naturall branches or Church members. Were they refuſed by the Apoſtles, or caſt off, or did they eject &amp; caſt out themſelves from being branches of the true Olive? Chriſts coming in the fleſh not diſcerned by them, was the occaſion of their fall from being the Iſrael of God: he was the ſtumbling ſtone and the rock of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that made them fall from their Church ſtate and relation. They would
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:42522:60"/>not own any other adminiſtration but that of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and upon that account undid themſelves and periſhed. What think you would have been the iſſue, had they owned Jeſus Chriſt to be the true Meſſias, and ſo had come under the Goſpell adminiſtrations, as ours are; and would not be under any other, that they ſhould have been refuſed and ſeparated from, as being none of the Church of Chriſt? I beſeech you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it: did not thouſands of the Jewes come in and offer themſelves to Baptiſme at the preaching of one ſhort word or ſermon, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. And can we imagine that they were all true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts in your ſenſe? was any refuſed that deſired to be one in the Chriſtian profeſſion? Suppoſe that all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people in <hi>England</hi> were unbapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed (as ſome reproachfully and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly report they are) and were ſenſible of that condition: and ſhould come and deſire Baptiſme upon no other account then their preſent capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city would admit of; confeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſinners, and promiſing obedience to the word of God; profeſſing hope of mercy and happineſſe through the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:42522:60"/>merits of Jeſus Chriſt (which all that have learned their Creed are capable to do) I would fain know whether you could lawfully refuſe to baptize them at the preſent, without any long defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it, although they had been Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens born. I would I did but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand your anſwer to this ſuppoſition. I conceive that all thoſe that being of years, are in a capacity for Baptiſme, are in a capacity alſo of all other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an communion. I preſume the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles baptized upon as eaſie termes, and ſo might you; except you have a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent commiſſion, or underſtand the Apoſtles commiſſion in ſome other ſenſe then they themſelves did. But I muſt contract my ſelf, &amp; aske you once again, whether you ever found any preſident in the Word for what you practiſe in this point? what Church under the adminiſtration of the Goſpell will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford a preſident for your practiſe? Do you ſeparate according to Apoſtolicall order and rule, or by vertue of ſome new commiſſion or light the Scriptures ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taught you? I pray you again conſider: you had need be ſure of good warrant to bear you out: for you have
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:42522:61"/>been the cauſe and means of our being without diſcipline, Sacraments, union and communion with other refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches: indulgence to you hath been the occaſion of an unlimited To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, the miſery of all thoſe facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Schiſmes, Hereſies, Blaſphemies now abounding in every corner of the Land. Well, if your foundation be only the wiſdome of the fleſh, and a worldly intereſt, time will diſcover more of the Babel you are building: when the conſequences of your prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, practiſe and deſign are come to full maturity. It may come to that paſſe (and it is much to be feared it will) that you would retreat if you could tell how. In the mean time the wilde beaſts of the wilderneſſe come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods vineyard, and by hereſies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the tender grapes: <hi>and many follow their pernicious wayes, by reaſon of whom the way of truth is evill ſpoken of. Men ariſe from among our ſelves ſpeaking per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe things to draw away Diſciples after them,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.2. Act. 20.30. <hi>But mark them thut cauſe diviſions and avoid them,</hi> Rom. 16.17.</p>
            <p>But let me ſpeak one word more in
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:42522:61"/>order to diſcipline, which as you were never yet willing to come under as to the reforming of the whole, ſo have your indevours been all along moſt fierce to obſtruct and retard the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline debated on in order to that end.</p>
            <p>Again, when the fitteſt way in Chriſtian prudence, according to rule was agreed upon as a means to reforme the whole; and confirmed by the ſupreme Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Nation: deſigns were dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on to obſtruct it, and ſuch things attempted, as are the greateſt ſcandals to the Proteſtant Religion that ever it ſuffered under.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, notwithſtanding many ſymptomes and ſad omens of a carnall deſign tending to the confuſion and ruine of the whole (and thoſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per products of your own miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages) do already appear; yet you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in your own contrivances, and will not retract, untill not only the Church, but alſo the flouriſhing ſtate of the Common wealth be invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the ſame confuſion and ruine. The very ſinewes of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth are the fear of God, and divine order in carrying on the ſame in all
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:42522:62"/>its parts uniformly: different parties and factions too much indulged do ever beget jealouſies and fears, the common nurſery of ſedition and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion: And that which cannot be held without gratifying of all factions and parties, cannot in reaſon and policy hold long. Why may not men truly fear God, and carry on the power of godlineſſe in their ſeveral functions and places, under an eſtabliſhment of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, worſhip and order; the only way to honour God? And the beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to preſerve the whole unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in the Church is a good founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of peace and tranquillity in the Common-wealth. And that is ever the beſt policy amongſt Chriſtians that is ſubordinate to true piety: and our greateſt freedome deſired, will be ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt attained in the way of religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when ſin will be a ſnare to any people. I confeſſe it is meerly occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally that ſome things have drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from my pen of this nature. I would not offend any, nor have I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to meddle with the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent way ſtrictly taken; they have been ſufficiently anſwered by divers
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:42522:62"/>learned and reverend Gentlemen: and the inconſiſtences, contradictions, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities and miſtakes of their way diſcovered, and not y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t vindicated by any that ever I heard of. I only have hinted ſome things tending (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) to the Churches peace and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in vindicating Church members from reproach and ſlander, and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the preceding diſcourſe. And therefore I ſhall end with Mr. <hi>Humphreys</hi> wiſhes, adding ſome of mine own.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I wiſh we had a government eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht in the Church, the neareſt in Chriſtian prudence that may be to the word of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I wiſh the duty of fraternall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reption, a watching over, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing one another in love were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter known and practiſed amongſt us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I wiſh that men would look more to their own conſciences, and leave the judging of others ſpirits, heart and reins alone to the judgement ſeat of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I wiſh, though there may be ſome judging by the fruits, that wiſe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men would be more cautious of countenancing the ſeparations in the viſible Church, ſeeing upon the ſame
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:42522:63"/>ground that you go to gather a Church out of any mixt congregation, another will gather a ſeparation out of your Church; and ſo continue (as I have intimated from our ſad experience) an endleſſe ſeparating, untill this firſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration ſhall in a few years be able to take up the ſaying of that greateſt Grand-mother, unto thoſe many Schiſmes ſhee ſhall ſee iſſuing as her naturall off-ſpring, out of her owne bowels, Riſe up daughter, go to thy daughter, for thy daughters daughter has a daughter; for this ſeparations ſeparation has a ſeparation; ſo farre Mr. <hi>Humfrey:</hi> I adde.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I wiſh that the diſtinction of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers and unbeleevers, Church and world, Chriſt and Belial, holy and profane, worthy Church members, and unworthy, were uſed in the Church of God according to Scripture mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and with due caution, and no otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I wiſh that Sacraments were more clearly underſtood in reſpect of their nature and end, attributing unto them their due according to the Scripture, avoiding all humane boldneſſe, either
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:42522:63"/>in adding to advance them, or in dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing them ſo as in the leaſt degree to debaſe them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I wiſh that the Lord Jeſus may have the liberty and full ſcope of his own inſtituted ordinances given for the ſpirituall good of his Church; that he may uſe them as inſtruments of his Spirit in order to that end, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſpirits of all his ſubjects, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their neceſſities and ſpirituall wants.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I wiſh that a godly care may be taken in the education of all borne in the Church, that being inſtructed in the plaineſt way of faith and obedience in the Chriſtian religion, they may be prepared to profit by every ordinance in the Church when they come to years.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I wiſh that all of years may be made to underſtand their duties and Church priviledges and be incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged unto Church communion in all the waies of Chriſt; that ſo they may come under Church diſcipline, the beſt remedy to reclaim the obſtinate and wilfull offenders.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I wiſh the gifted brethren were
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:42522:64"/>better imployed, then in unchurching our Churches, and gathering Churches out of them: it were a work more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and acceptable, either to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to exerciſe their gifts to the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and building up of that Church in which they received them; or elſe to goe into the infidell world (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did) and preach the Goſpel and plant Churches there.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:42522:64"/>
            <head>The Scripture Raile Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</head>
            <p>REader, ſince I parted with what I had written in anſwer to Doctor <hi>Drake</hi> in the foregoing diſcourſe; there came to my hand Mr. <hi>Humfreys</hi> Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in vindication of himſelf; a work very well performed by him: wherein the truth formerly by him aſſerted is better cleared, and confirmed, to the ſatisfaction of many ſouls fearing God, and breathing forth their ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſires after the ſettlement, refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and uniformity of the Church of God in <hi>England</hi> according to the Word of God. Be not prejudiced againſt his book by other learned men, who have and ſtill do appear with much bitterneſſe and paſſion againſt him; more to affright with words and humane dictates meerly, then with mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:42522:65"/>of grounded truth, according to the ſenſe of the holy Scripture: witneſſe that book put forth by ſome Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire,</hi> intituled, <hi>A Scripture Raile to the Communion Table.</hi> I confeſſe the title is good; for we do acknowledge there ought to be ſuch a thing; but not in their ſenſe, as I hope ſhall appear by the diſcovery made in this ſhort diſcourſe following, in which I ſhall wave what hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready written in anſwer to <hi>D. Drake,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Humfrey</hi> and my ſelf, and take notice only of ſome things in the <hi>Scripture Raile</hi> which have not yet been ſpoken to, that I know of. And this I ſhall do as briefly as I can, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would not anticipate him whom it doth more nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all, becauſe I would not leave the weak and incautelous Reader deceived with vain and groundleſſe words in reading this <hi>Scripture Raile,</hi> let this be noted, that I take Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture diſcipline to be the only Rail for the Communion Table; which (I hope) both the Author reproached, and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:42522:65"/>my ſelf earneſtly deſire may be ſet up; and all our indevours tend as condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible means to that end; as being aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the firſt ſtone in the building of the reformation, (as to our caſe) is holy diſcipline: And whether their principles or ours tend moſt to that, I hope to make appear to ſober and unprejudiced Chriſtians. And the way I ſhall take, ſhall be to diſcover ſome of theſe Gentlemens unbrotherly dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with Mr. <hi>Humfrey:</hi> firſt in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting his ſenſe. Secondly, in ſetting up a Raile to the Lords Table, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting Scripture, and ſo making that Raile to be a pretended diſcipline meerly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They have damned and cenſured his Book to be an ungodly pamphlet, in which is a maſſe of perverting Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, tending to deſtroy all Church reformation; little better then carnall and profane reaſoning, ſophiſtry, a heterodox piece, abomination, a vile piece, with divers other ſuch hard cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; language enough to affright any from ever looking into it, that have any care of their ſouls, to avoid their own deſtruction, in complying
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:42522:66"/>with that ſoul damning practiſe of maintaining mixt communion, as they call it.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſſe theſe men ſeem very confident in reproaching and cenſuring both the Book and the man: but in this their indeavour to make it thus vile and odious to the world, they have not the leaſt evidence of truth or ſtrength of reaſon to evince it, that I can finde in their Book: And it will ſo appear, if you minde what is Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſcope and end in his diſcourſe, and what are the principles upon which it is founded. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the viſible Church of Chriſt conſiſts of men making a profeſſion of faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo are Saints by calling, what ever they are in truth, while they ſo profeſſe, and adhere to the true worſhip, the means and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of which are hearing the word, receiving the Sacrament, and prayer: and of theſe many are called and few are choſen.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all of theſe of years come under the obligation of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and are bound to do their duty &amp; homage to Chriſt their Lord, as well
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:42522:66"/>as they can, according to <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all ſuch ought to ſubmit to Church diſcipline, and not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from any obſervance, nor deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any Church priviledge, untill they be judicially proceeded againſt, and debarred by vertue of poſitive excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That Miniſters by vertue of their function and office may lawfully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Sacraments to Church members, though they be ignorant and ſcandalous, he doing his duty as well as he may in preparing them, in the want of Church diſcipline. Theſe (I dare boldly affirme) are the main things aſſerted in that little deſpiſed piece; which with a ſober ſpirit, the Author hath ſoberly diſcuſſed and cleared from the common exceptions made againſt it by men of different mindes: for which his pains firſt and laſt, I verily beleeve the Church of God in <hi>England</hi> have great cauſe to be thankfull to the Lord of the harveſt, for ſending ſuch a faithfull plain-hearted labourer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us: the ſweet temperature of his ſpirit, ſo adorned with wiſdome,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:42522:67"/>charity, and ſuch a peaceable frame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaks him taught of God the true ſenſe of his will in his holy Scriptures, rather then his reproachers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Touching the viſible Church, what evill hath he done in aſſerting it, to conſiſt of men making a profeſſion of faith in Chriſt? Wherein doth he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the moſt orthodox writers in all ages, in judging the Church of <hi>England</hi> a true Church? It is confeſſed by the adverſaries; and alſo that a parochiall congregation where the Word is truly preached, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments adminiſtred according to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, being a part of the whole, is a true Church likewiſe. And this is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo confeſſed by theſe Gentlemen; for they grant that our parochiall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are true Churches in a large ſenſe, and that is enough as to this; and ſo I hope there is no evill in this firſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the next thing by him aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, namely, that all of years in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, being baptized, come under the obligation of all Chriſts commands; it is proved by the text before cited, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. And that in order to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:42522:67"/>the Lords Supper, <hi>Do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me,</hi> is a known duty belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to every particular member of the Church in common with all other parts of the worſhip and ſervice of God. And is it then profane reaſoning to urge Church members to do their duty and homage, in this particular more then in all others? To this theſe Gentlemen have ſaid but little (that I can finde) to take off what is urged by Mr. <hi>H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for that of the Paſſeover, Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath the better end of the ſtaffe; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the duty of all to obſerve it in the ſeaſon under penalty of their lives up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wilfull neglect. <hi>Numb.</hi> 9.13. And If any, by reaſon of legall uncleanneſſe, or being in a journey a far off, could not keep the Paſſeover the fourteenth day of the firſt moneth, they were to keep it the fourteenth day of the ſecond moneth, and ſo nothing would excuſe any in the not obſerving that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſee verſ. 10.11. And beſides, that legall uncleanneſſe did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barre them from the Paſſeover more then from any other obſervance of communion ſacred or civill.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:42522:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:42522:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:42522:69"/>
            <p>It is pity theſe Gentlemen ſhould be in ſuch haſte, that they could not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the many places of Scripture which have been brought by others (as they ſay pag. 28.) to prove that the Jewes were kept from the paſſeover for morall uncleanneſſe or ſcandalous ſins; which they are confident neither M. <hi>H.</hi> nor all the world can ever anſwer. For my part I wonder what Scriptures thoſe are, that I ſhould never ſee nor read them in the Bible. Theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quote four texts (as I take it) to prove the ſame; to which I ſhall ſpeak ſomething particularly.</p>
            <p>The firſt text is <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.30, 31. Where by Gods appointment, the ſoul ſinning preſumptuouſly was to be cut off from among his people; namely by death; and ſo from all other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances as well as the Paſſeover. And for the unclean perſon that would not ſubmit to the law of purification, he was to be cut off from the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iſrael; and therefore from all communion in worſhip, <hi>Numb.</hi> 19, 20.</p>
            <p>And putting out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.22. was to be put out of the Jewes and Gentiles, and ſo from
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:42522:69"/>all ordinances of worſhip; beſides the Synagogues were not the place of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the feaſt of the paſſeover. And what then is there yet in all this to prove that for morall uncleanneſſe ſome were to be kept from the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over only?</p>
            <p>But let us come to the next place, which is <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.8. Where (they ſay) whoſoever would not come to build the Temple within three daies, ſhould be ſeparated from the congregation, and conſequently excluded from the paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over. This place, that it might ſeem to be for their purpoſe, is corrupted by them, and falſly alledged. The words are part of that proclamation agreed upon by the heads of the people after their return from captivity to Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; concerning that great ſin of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſtrange wives, whoſoever would not come within the three daies accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the counſell of the Princes and the Elders of the people, all his ſubſtance ſhould be forfeited, and himſelf ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the congregation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now was this to come to build the Temple? no, it was to confeſſe their ſins, and to put away their ſtrange wives, that the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:42522:70"/>wrath of the Lord might be turned away. This Scripture will ſerve my turn her eaſter better then theirs now.</p>
            <p>But the next Scripture they alledge is <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. <hi>Her Prieſts have viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my law, and have profaned my holy things: they have put no difference between the holy and profane, the clean and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean.</hi> Now by holy and profane (we know) is uſually meant the circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and the uncircumciſed; and ſo clean and unclean is to be taken in a legall ſenſe: and then what is this to debarring from the Paſſeover for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall uncleanneſſe and ſcandalous ſins, more then from other obſervances?</p>
            <p>But they ſay further, that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed in heart were not to enter into the Sanctuary to pollute it; and for this they quote <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.7, 9. where again they groſly abuſe the Text, and that wilfully too, as one may think. And truly I cannot but wonder that men pretending to ſuch purity of worſhip and diſcipline, dare make ſo bold with Scriptures, as purpoſely to pervert them to blinde the eyes of the reader that he may not underſtand the ſenſe; telling him that ſuch as did manifeſtly
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:42522:70"/>appear to be uncircumciſed in heart, though they had received the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of the fleſh, might not enter into the Sanctuary; and that the admitting of ſuch into the Sanctuary, was the fault for which the Prieſts were puniſhed, verſ. 13. A moſt notorious falſhood, and (if they did look upon the text) wilfully aſſerted to deceive their reader. The thing the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of in this place, was that they had brought into Gods Sanctuary, not Jewes, but ſtrangers or aliens, uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed in heart: and that we might be ſure it is meant of Gentiles and not Jewes, there is added uncircumciſed in the fleſh to pollute the Sanctuary, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Law; but this theſe men leave out, and conceal from the reader; which if they could alſo have daſht out of the Bible, I beleeve it would be the ſtrongeſt place in the Bible for their purpoſe; but being as it is, it makes nothing at all for them or againſt Mr. <hi>H.</hi> And we may take notice of the juſt judgement of God upon theſe mens ſpirits, leaving them to miſcarry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that wittingly, in pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:42522:71"/>the Scriptures; the thing they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly charge that reverent man Mr. <hi>H.</hi> with.</p>
            <p>But to leave their ſalfe gloſſes on theſe places and go on; they tell us further pag. 30. That this ſpoken of the Sanctuary is typicall in reference to the ſpirituall Sanctuary, the Church of Chriſt in Goſpell times: but how they will prove that the Sanctuary was a type of the Church of God in our times, I confeſſe I know not; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Jewes were a Goſpell Church and under the Goſpell Covenant then, as well as we now. <hi>To them was the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell preached as well as to us,</hi> Heb. 4.2.</p>
            <p>But from thoſe Scriptures they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the Jews were kept from the Paſſeover for preſumptuous and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſins; for ſay they, If they were cut off from the congregation, then they came not to the Paſſeover; And one end of their cutting off was, that they might not defile the Paſſeover; and thence conclude that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath deluded the reader.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let them for ſhame be more ſingle hearted hereafter in their conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:42522:71"/>This is their argument, ſome Jewes were to be cut off from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation by death for preſumptuous and ſcandalous ſins; therefore ſome were to be debarred the Paſſcover for morall uncleanneſſe: is this a good conſequence? That by cutting off from the congregation we are (for the moſt part at leaſt) to underſtand a cutting off by death, appears, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.30, 31. <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.14. Again, they were cut off, ſtoned to death for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſins; therefore they were cut off that they might not defile the Paſſeover: This in plain termes is all that they ſay; and is this good and ſound reaſoning? Is not this a great diſcovery of Mr. <hi>Humſreys</hi> deluding the reader? And let me note ſurther, that if it could be proved that any were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the Sanctuary for ſcandalous ſins; the conſequence will be no more but this, That for ſcandalous ſins ſome may be excluded from all the parts of Gods worſhip, which is not denied but granted by Mr. <hi>H.</hi> provided it be done by the juſt cenſures of the Church: ſo that theſe Gentlemen may ſee, what a noiſe they make about no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:42522:72"/>
            <p>But they go on and tell us what <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſpy</hi> ſaith on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. (in his Book called <hi>Aarons Rod budded</hi>) concerning thoſe Iſraelites that did eat of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, and drank of the Rock that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them, that they falling into ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, whoredomes, murmurings, and the like, the wrath of God came upon them; hence they inferre, They did not eat of the Manna and drink of the Rock after the committing of thoſe ſins, and ſo were excluded for morall uncleanneſſe; as good a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as the former.</p>
            <p>For firſt, I deny that all that were guilty of thoſe ſins were cut off from the congregation: for the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation murmured, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet were they not all deſtroyed; their carkaſſes fell in the wilderneſſe not all at once in one day, but by degrees for many years: and yet thoſe that were ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red did eat Manna, otherwiſe they muſt needs have periſhed with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For thoſe that were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and cut off, was it that they might not eat Manna any more? What a ſtrange, and abſurd conſequence is
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:42522:72"/>this; They were deſtroyed for their idolatry, whoredomes and murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, therefore they were cut off that they might not eat of that Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Manna. What a ſtrange fancy is this? as if a malefactor were put to death, that he might not live to come to the Sacrament any more; me thinks it were more rationall to ſay, they were cut off by death, that they might not diſhonour God by the committing of thoſe ſins of idolatry, whoredomes and murmurings any more.</p>
            <p>In the ſame page, from the falſe and abſurd premiſes (as they are already diſcovered to be) thoſe Gentlemen urge Mr. <hi>H.</hi> with an argument; but it is ſo long, flat and falſe, that I ſhall paſſe it by, having already cut the legs it ſtands upon. And the truth is, the Author whom they reproach, hath ſaid enough concerning this Scripture to ſtop the mouth of very malice and envie it ſelf, if any thing would do it.</p>
            <p>But let us remember what we are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Theſe Gentlemen have denied that all the Iſraelites were admitted to their Sacraments, eſpecially the Paſſeover: and to prove this, they have brought
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:42522:73"/>ſome Scriptures: I have examined them (you ſee) and their interences and concluſions drawn from them: and all they have ſaid and make a ſhew of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to no more but this; 1. That ſome were denyed the Paſſeover for a moneths ſpace by reaſon of their le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall uncle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nneſſe. 2. That ſome have been cut off by death for morall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, or that ſome have otherwiſe been ſeparated from the congregation, and ſo from all ordinances of divine worſhip, for ſcandalous ſins. And all that can poſſibly be gathered hence, is no more then what Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath all along granted: for he excepts the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate in his <hi>Free Admiſſion to the Lords Supper:</hi> and this is by them yeelded unto, if he mean right accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word, the matter is ended. So that one would think they granted this, and in another place, that our parochiall congregations are true Churches in a large ſenſe, that the whole difference between Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and them were only in point of diſcipline: And if ſo, then the fault Mr. <hi>H.</hi> is charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with in this point, is his not ſetting up diſcipline, but exerciſing the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:42522:73"/>of worſhip without it. But M. <hi>Joanes</hi> hath ſaid enough to take off this, in urging and proving a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of adminiſtring the Sacrament of the Supper, in congregations not Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. Thus we have conſidered the admiſſion to the Paſſeover among the Jewes.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing there is ſuch analogie between the Paſſeover and the Lords Supper; the admiſſion to the one ſeems to be a good rule for admiſſion to the other; and ſeems to be granted on both ſides, in that it is urged by both. And therefore I ſhal aſſert ſome things from the law of the Paſſeover, for further confirmation and ſtrengthning of the duty of free admiſſion to the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Paſſeover was the ſame for ſubſtance with the holy Supper, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the ſame things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was a ſervice commanded the whole Church, that whoſoever ſhould neglect it in his ſeaſon ſhould be cut off from his people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The people of Iſrael were a mixt people, and many of them as uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of making a ſpirituall uſe of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:42522:74"/>the Paſſeover, as ours of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Church under the Goſpell adminiſtration is under the ſame Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and is but added to or graffed into the Church of the Jewes, and their conſtitution, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.18.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Church of Chriſt, ſince the comming of Chriſt in the fleſh, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame principles, and in ſome reſpects greater then under <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets. And therefore why ſhould not admiſſion to the Lords Supper be as free as the Paſſeover.</p>
            <p>Firſt I ſay the Jewes Paſſeover was the ſame for ſubſtance with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper, both ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the ſame things?</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Paſchal Lamb appointed for that holy ſervice, was a lively type of the Lamb of God ſlain from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, to take away the ſins thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The offering of this Lamb whole without diſmembring or breaking a bone of him, did ſhew that whole Chriſt muſt ſuffer, that his ſuffering might be ſufficient to ſatisfie divine juſtice.</p>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:42522:74"/>
            <p n="3">3. The bloud of the lamb was to be ſtricken on the lintels and ſide poſts of every ones door, as a token upon thoſe houſes where the Iſraelites were; that when the Lord paſſed through the land of <hi>Egypt</hi> to deſtroy the firſt born both of man and beaſt, the plague might not ſmite thoſe houſes: which was to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them, that this Lamb of God Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe bloud was ſhed upon the croſſe, was the only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of his Church and people from the wrath which the Egyptian world lies under: and not having any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him, nor means of coming unto him, muſt needs periſh. And all this concerning the Paſſeover was to be obſerved yearly at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, through their generations for ever, for a memoriall of their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> which though it were but bodily and temporall, yet it was to lead them to the underſtanding of their ſpirituall and eternall delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance by the bloud of Chriſt. And hence it is that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Chriſt our Paſſeover is ſacrificed for us,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.7. We in the Supper have the ſigns of Chriſts own death, held out as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:42522:75"/>accompliſhed; they in the type had him held forth as decreed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be accompliſhed; and both to be obſerved in that remembrance. And as it is well obſerved, that Chriſt having kept the laſt Paſſeover, did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately inſtitute the Sacrament of the Supper, that it might ſucceed in the room and ſtead of the Paſſeover. A change in the thing typified (Chriſt then to come and ſuffer death, now already come and ſuffered) was the cauſe of the change in the externals of this ſervice.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That the Law of the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, was of abſolute force in reſpect of all the congregation of Iſrael, is ſo obvious and manifeſt, that I need not ſay any thing for proof thereof: <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. &amp; <hi>Numb.</hi> 9. is without all gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying. And though the end of that obſervance were ſpirituall and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice it ſelf myſterious; yet thoſe that were moſt ignorant and carnall, were as much under the obligation of that holy ſervice, as thoſe that were rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and really holy: it concerned them all to conforme to the externals of that ſervice upon their lives; no
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:42522:75"/>excuſe would ſerve for the omiſſion of it, but that of legall uncleanneſſe and being in a journey, and that but for the preſent only.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That the Church of the Jewes was a mixt people, in reſpect of reall goodneſſe and badneſſe, even as ours are, I know none will deny; and yet in reſpect of their relative ſtate, in reference to the Covenant made with their fathers, they were all equals in the enjoyment of the externall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and obſervances of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the Church of God, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to that bleſſedneſſe promiſed to all that diligently obſerved the duties of the Covenant. And no people ſo happy and proſperous as they, while they adhered to Gods worſhip pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed unto them: but when they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the waies of God, and followed their own waies, and went after other gods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then it ever went ill with them. I know the Lord required truth and power, as well as externall form in worſhip, yet they are not uſually blamed for want of power, but for want of form in not doing what God commanded.</p>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:42522:76"/>
            <p n="4">4. That the ſeverall Churches of the Gentiles now, are under the ſame Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace, and added to, or graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed into the Church of the Jewes and their Church conſtitution; I think can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied. For though the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Covenant now be different from what it was before Chriſt was exhibited; yet there is no more change of the Church properly and formally conſidered, then there is change of the Covenant; or change of the head Chriſt, the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever, on whom (as the chief corner ſtone) the Church in all ages hath been and ſtill is built and founded. The ſame perſons that by birth priviledge were born members of the Jewes Church, and beleeving in Chriſt kept their ſtation, were alwaies members, they and their ſeed never ceaſing ſo to be, even thouſands of the Jewes. Jeſus Chriſt had many Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, while he himſelf was a member and a Prophet of that Church, and conformed unto the ceremoniall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration. The twelve whom he choſe were before (moſt of them) mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Jewiſh Church: and though
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:42522:76"/>not after the order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> yet after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> (as being King and Lord of all) he gave them authority to preach and baptize and work miracles in the Jewiſh Church only, while he was converſant among them. And thoſe that beleeved in him, and thoſe that beleeved not, were all one Church, adhering to the ſame worſhip and order of that Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Chriſt was raiſed from the dead; and had compleated the work of mans redemption: then all thoſe carnall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances were aboliſhed; he put an end to them all: and thoſe that never did beleeve that he was the true Meſſias, did then unchurch themſelves and their ſeed. For they ſtill adhering unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and looking upon Chriſt as a falſe Chriſt, refuſed to ſubmit to the adminiſtration of the Lord Jeſus; and ſo loſt their ſtation in the Church: but ſo many as were convinced that he was the true Meſſias, adhered unto the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Doctrine, and came under all Church adminiſtrations: ſo that for a good ſpace of time the Apoſtles prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Lord Jeſus in <hi>Jury</hi> only, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they preached to the Gentiles; ſo
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:42522:77"/>that there was I beleeve many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of ſouls of the newly reformed Church of the Jewes, before there were any particular Churches of the Gentiles. And where it is ſaid, they were added to the Church, it is not to be underſtood, that here was now a new Church conſtituted where was none before; but ſtill the ſame Church under a different adminiſtration: And the Jewes that were of the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, beleeving in Chriſt, as in him that was promiſed ſhould come, are now by the preaching of the Apoſtles convinced, that Jeſus whom their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers crucified, is the Chriſt already come. And this beleeving of theirs was no new faith, but the ſame which they had before in reſpect of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, though under another conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And for thoſe Jewes which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved and adhered to the Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, many of them for a great while would not be taken off from their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer cuſtomes and obſervations. It is ſaid, that <hi>ſalvation is of the Jewes,</hi> Joh. 4.22. <hi>Out of Sion ſhall go forth the Law, and the Word of the Lord from Jeruſalem,</hi> Iſa. 2.3. After Chriſts aſcenſion, the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:42522:77"/>Apoſtles were to preach the God to all nations, but beginning firſt at Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.47. And they that were ſcattered abroad upon the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that aroſe about <hi>Stephen,</hi> travelled as far as <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Cyprus</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> preaching the Word to none but the Jewes only, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.19.</p>
            <p>Certainly the Jewes were the firſt that came under the Goſpell Miniſtry; and although ſome of them did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, yet that did not make the faith of God of none effect; that did not deprive the beleevers of their Church ſtate, nor make void the promiſes of God made to them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.3. The faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of God appeared in the effects of great Covenant love to that people, in opening the eyes and hearts of ſo many thouſands to receive the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell. There were but ſome of the branches that were broken off, and not all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the Gentiles received all from the Jewes; they were the only inſtruments of their converſion: there being few or none in authority to preach but ſuch as were Jewes by nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at firſt. All this being ſo, it muſt
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:42522:78"/>needs follow, that the beleeving Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles were but added to, or graffed into the Church of the Jewes; and baptized into the ſame body, and ſo made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the ſame hope and calling, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made the children of the ſame God; fellow heirs, and of the ſame body, and partakers with them of his promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.6. Fellow citizens with the Saints (the beleeving Jewes) and of the houſhold of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19.</p>
            <p>And true it is, that the Churches of the Gentiles had a very reverent eſteem of the Church of the Jewes; and did readily conform to the directions of the Church at Jeruſalem: and were care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their charity, to gather and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute to their neceſſity; confeſſing themſelves their debtors, having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from them their ſpirituall things, and that alone by their means, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.26, 27. So that all make up but one Church; and all walk by the ſame rule; having one faith, one Lord, one Baptiſme: All ſubmitted themſelves to the rule and order of the Apoſtles, they undertaking the care and order of all Churcher. All the Churches of the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:42522:78"/>Gentiles were not only converted to the faith by the Apoſtles, but alſo put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an holy order and way by ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them officers to rule and feed them in the Lord. And as it was in the Jewes Church under <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, there was a receiving of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes, aliens converted, and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Jewes by religion; ſo it was in the times of the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtles; they made nations and cities and countreys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes, and they became Chriſtians with the Jewes, and there was but one law, rule and way for all that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e imbodied into the Church. And there was gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> off from the ſame Church ſtill all along to this day. I have been too long in this, but I will be ſhorter in the next.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, that the Church of Chriſt ſince the coming of Chriſt in the fleſh is under the ſame, and in ſome reſpects, greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riviledges, then under <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes</hi> and the Prophets. This will appear to be a truth., if we con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>der th<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Jeſus Chriſt is and ever was the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ule of all bleſſings and privil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dges unto the Church in all times and ages of the world, that the Church hath
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:42522:79"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:42522:79"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:42522:80"/>ever been in poſſeſſion or expectation of. On the account of his tranſaction with the Father, all the promiſes of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant bleſſings of grace and glory, made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed, are founded and thereby confirmed; and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to all that are of his faith; for ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>They that are of the faith are bleſſed with faithfull</hi> Abraham; even all the Gentiles that receive the Doctrine of faith, ſo as to initiate them into that Church of which <hi>Abraham</hi> was the father; it being firſt formed up in his family, and the Govenant freely made with him, and ſealed to him by the Sacrament of Circumciſion: I ſay all that are of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith are bleſſed with him. Hence it is that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> hath many expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to the ſame purpoſe. Chap. 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed be God who hath bleſſed us with all ſpirituall bleſſings in Chriſt.</hi> And in the ſecond chapter it is clearly intimated, that there was a time, while they were in their ſtate of Paganiſme. that they were <hi>Aliens from the Common wealth of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, ſtrangers from the Covenants of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, without hope, and without God in the world: But now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>you that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:42522:80"/>off, are made nigh by the bloud of Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 2.11, 12, 13. But now in Chriſt Jeſus you are of the Commonwealth of Iſrael, children of the Covenants and Promiſes; and have as much inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt &amp; hope of good from God through Chriſt, as the Jewes who by deſcent were the naturall ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi> And therefore were now <hi>no more ſtrangers and foreiners, but fellow Citizens with the Saints and of the houſhold of God,</hi> verſ. 19. The reaſon of all is, Chriſt is the ſame yeſterday and to day and for ever in ſpirituall things, as to the Church and their ſeed. And therefore he is ſaid <hi>to be the Miniſter of circumciſion, for the truth of God, to confirme the promiſes made to the fathers, and that the Gentiles might glorifie God for his mercies,</hi> Rom. 15.8, 9. as being made ſharers in all thoſe promiſes of free grace made to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and their naturall ſeed. Nay, we may obſerve, how the Apoſtles do uſually apply the ſeverall promiſes in the Prophets to particular caſes in the Churches of Chriſt in their times.</p>
            <p>But it may be asked,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> what were the priviledges of the Jewes Church under <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets?</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:42522:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:42522:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:42522:82"/>
            <p>The Law of the Paſſeover did oblige all the congregation of Iſrael upon their lives to obſerve it in the ſeaſon. Our Supper of the Lord is the ſame to us that the Paſſeover was to them, for the ſubſtance (as hath been proved) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame meaning and end. The people of the Jewes as mixt as ours are, if not worſe in reſpect of good and bad, regenerate and unregenerate: and ſo as uncapable to make a ſpirituall uſe thereof. The Church under the Law and the Prophets before the coming of Chriſt in the fleſh and ſince the ſame; which Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles only reformed in point of externall adminiſtration, firſt owned by the Jewes: unto which Church ſo refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, all beleeving Gentiles are added, and graffed into it as the ſtock; and ſo partake of the ſame ſpirituall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall priviledges with them, they and their ſeed, ſo long as they continue to adhere and cleave to the outward means of ſalvation, in order to that end: and from theſe premiſes will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low theſe concluſions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the ſame obligation lies now upon all Chriſtians to obſerve
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:42522:82"/>the Ordinance of the holy Supper, that did lie upon the whole congregation of Iſrael to obſerve the Ordinance of the Paſſeover; and the Law of the Paſſeover may teach us ſo much; and in ſome reſpect is ſtill in force. For ſo long as the equity and reaſon of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or law remains, the command and law it ſelf remains for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it: but the equity and reaſon of that command concerning the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over ſtill remains in reſpect of the Lords Supper ſucceeding in the room of the Paſſeover; and therefore ſhould guide and direct us in the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, as touching the ſubjects or perſons that ought to receive.</p>
            <p>And then ſecondly, if all that were in the Church of the Jewes, came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obligation of all the commands of God to that Church, reſpecting the members in common; and that both good and bad; then all that are graſſed into the ſame Church, come under the obligation of all the Lawes given to the ſame Church, and reſpecting the members in common, now as well as then, even all good and bad.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the ſame exceptions that
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:42522:83"/>which all (as he hath ſtated the thing) are bound to obſerve.</p>
            <p>I need not ſtand upon this,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> becauſe I have already been ſomewhat large up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Scripture, (where they ſay the Apoſtle requires ſuch qualifications) in my former diſcourſe, to which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerre the reader. Yet becauſe theſe men have ſomething which the Doctor hath not, I ſhall hint a little at ſomething of theirs. I muſt confeſſe I judge the main ſtreſſe of the controverſie to lie in that eleventh chapter of the firſt to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> And there need be no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were injoyned by the Apoſtle to obſerve this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the holy Supper in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Chriſt: for verſ. 2. he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends them for remembring him in all things, and keeping the ordinances as he delivered them to them. So that their keeping and obſerving of this ordinance, as well as the other (as to the thing it ſelf) was well done by them: but then when he ſpeaks to their miſcarriages about the manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, he praiſes them not, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves them, for their wofull abuſe of the ordinance in their exceſſe, diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:42522:83"/>and unreverent behaviour in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry act of receiving, or while they were together for that end: They made a breach upon the very externals of that ſervice; uſing the elements as common things to pleaſe the outward man, and not to that end for which the Lord Jeſus appointed them. And theſe men (in a manner) confeſſe as much, that they being newly come out of idolatry, in imitation of their idolatrous feaſts had their love-feaſts, when they came to the Lords Supper, and that there was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe among them, though not preciſely at the Lords Supper. Theſe men are not willing to yeeld they were drunk at the adminiſtration preciſely, but immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately before; or if at the time of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, yet not with the wine conſecrated for that holy and ſpirituall end, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the death of Chriſt. And therefore (as moſt Divines conjecture) their exceſſe was at their love-feaſt ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in <hi>Jude.</hi> But I conceive it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uncertain whether they had any ſuch feaſt or no; that place in <hi>Jude</hi> doth not determine it; much leſſe the keeping of it immediately before the Lords Supper, or in the place where
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:42522:84"/>they met together for the celebration of that holy ſervice. But whether they came drunk, or eat and drank unto ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the elements liberally provided, it was ſuch a profaneneſſe that neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> nor Mr. <hi>H.</hi> I hope ſhall never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>: what ever theſe men charge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with in this reſpect, telling the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the admiſſion of idolaters, drunkards and impenitents to the Sacrament, pag 32.33, 34. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. But is this brotherly dealing (think you) to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke ſuch a wilde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a Miniſter ſhew what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or which God ſo ſeverely puniſhed the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> but he muſt be reproached as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne pleading for the admittance of idolaters, drunkards and impenitent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Sacrament? Hath not Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ſaid enough in his Book to free himſelf from this crime? He ſaid indeed there was nothing againſt their coming; for that was their duty, which theſe men deny, unleſſe they be ſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſied: but he doth not only ſay they ought to come, but to come prepared: yet mens impenitency and unprepared<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doth not make void the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God; neither is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:42522:84"/>to be neglected for an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſubſervient thereto.</p>
            <p>And I pray you, whom doth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſet up to be judge of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications in the Church? What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hath he appointed for this? Is it not clear that every man is to examine himſelf, and judge himſelf, that he may not be judged of the Lord? Can men deviſe better waies to carry on Gods Ordinances with purity, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n himſelf hath preſcribed? The <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rinthians</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, was in unworthy actions at the time of the adminiſtration: and I pray you who could foreſee that to prevent it better then themſelves? And as for their perſons and reall worthineſſe, the Apoſtle meddles not with it at all. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may we denomin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te men ſuch in perſon really, as ſome unworthy acts done by them do import: for if we do ſo, we ſhall condemn the generation of the juſt; righteous men may be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken with ſome unrighteous actions; <hi>for in many things we offend all,</hi> Jam. 3.2. And I grant this unworthy receiving was out of weakneſſe and ignorance (as theſe Gentlemen plead) the <hi>Corinthians</hi> coming newly out of their heatheniſm:
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:42522:85"/>but what is this to them that are not guilty of their unworthy receiving at all? as for matter of order and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent decorum in the obſervances, not one among a thouſand offending there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And for unworthineſſe of perſon, there is not one word in the Text, in reference to coming to the Sacrament, and yet that makes all the trouble, and cauſes many to run into a world of miſchief in the Church. Hence they inferre that the unregenerate in the Church, receiving, eat and drink judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to themſelves, and therefore teach them to omit the duty; contrary to all rule both in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and all Scripture Churches. And hence they make ſchiſmes and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Church. And hence they make this the higheſt ordinance, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a communion for Saints only; and upon the matter the leaſt of all in other reſpects; detracting from the wiſdome, power and goodneſſe of God, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be a means of regenerating grace unto Church members. And hence they have invented ſuſpenſion from the Lords Supper, with the loſſe or neglect of true diſcipline. And hence theſe
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:42522:85"/>tlemen have commended unto us, as the only expedient for reformation, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the minor part, leaving out the reſt (as judged to be excommunicable) without any tryall. Hence it is that many are afraid of being guilty in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking with others in their ſins, in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy receiving; eſpecially in the ſin of murdering Chriſt. And many other like errors they run into, by reaſon of this one error in taking that eating and drinking unworthily to be meant of unworthineſſe of perſon. The holy Ghoſt intends the manner of eating, but they will have it to be intended of the worthineſſe of the man that eats. And upon this error is grounded all that theſe men have to ſay againſt M. <hi>H.</hi> book. I could wiſh they would bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſider of it. For ſtill I ſay the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were commended for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this ordinance as well as any other in the Church; and reproved only for ſome great abuſe in their manner of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on that ſervice: the which abuſe did not lie in coming unworthily, nor in their other miſcarriages which were many upon other occaſions; but in this, their abuſing of the holy ſigns
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:42522:86"/>unto c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nall and common ends: <hi>For this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſickly amongſt them, an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> So that this place cannot be urged againſt any that are Chriſtians, and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nally (at leaſt) comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the holy actions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in this ſervice: but againſt open abuſes of the inſtitution.</p>
            <p>But theſe men will ſay of me,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> as they do of <hi>M. H.</hi> pag. 88 That I know well enough, but that I would blinde poor ſouls that [Do this in remembrance of me] was ſpoken to the Diſciples, ſuch as were of Chriſts family, and not to all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know ſure enough,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> that this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was ſpoken to the Diſciples of Chriſts family, not to all: but then I know alſo (and ſo might they) that all that are born in the Church of Chriſt and baptized, and of years, and under Church indulgence, are Diſciples of Chriſts family; and therefore that command is ſpoken to them; and they are bound to obſerve it, except they can produce ſome diſpenſation for the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of duty in this, more then in all other obſervances: for the baptized come under the obligation of doing all
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:42522:86"/>that Chriſt commands, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. And let the reader then judge, who are moſt guilty of blinding poor ſouls; they that teach them to obſerve and do all that Chriſt commands, or they that teach men to omit and neglect ſome ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary duties of homage and ſervice which Chriſt commands for the good of their ſouls; as theſe Gentlemen make very bold to do: but how they will anſwer it before their Maſter, I leave to themſelves to conſider. And when I ſay all ought to come, I do not mean the juſtly excommunicated, who while they are ſo, are out of Chriſts family; nor the unbaptized, as being againſt divine order; nor any that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Chriſtian Religion, caſting off the yoke of Chriſt in defiance of him, or the like.</p>
            <p>In the next place, I ſhall take notice how the Gentlemen do moſt notoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſe Mr. <hi>Humfreys</hi> ſenſe in a paſſage of his Book, telling their reader, That Mr. <hi>Humfrey</hi> ſaith, thoſe dreadfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the Apoſtle of being guilty of the body and bloud of Chriſt; and eating and drinking judgement to themſelves, were not to affright any
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:42522:87"/>from coming to the Sacrament: pag 39.</p>
            <p>But whoſoever ſhall but look into Mr. <hi>Humfreys</hi> Book, pag. 71. may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee what deſign theſe men have upon Mr. <hi>H.</hi> The truth is, be it right or wrong, they are reſolved (if poſſible) to render him odious to the inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, who are apt to beleeve every thing they hear from men that can but ſpeak ſmooth words, without further ſearch. And who would think that men of ſuch language, pretending ſo much to holineſſe and power of religion, ſhould dare to pervert and tear in pieces ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, that they might have ſomething to ſay againſt the Author, to render him odious to the worſt of men. Mr. <hi>H.</hi> words are theſe: <hi>It is certain thoſe dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full expreſsions, of being guilty of the bloud of Chriſt, and eating and drinking damnation; are to make men take heed that they prepare themſelves and come worthily: but</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I cannot think they are to affright any from the Sacrament.</hi> This is the reſult of what went before, where he urges both the principall duty and the acceſſory: we are bound to come; and to come worthily: If a man fail in the one, and be not ſufficiently prepared, I dare not
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:42522:87"/>ſay (ſaith he) that muſt keep him from the Sacrament: I am ſure it will not excuſe him from the other that is the principall duty. Beſides, they ſhould have remembred what Mr. <hi>H.</hi> laid down in ſtating his Free Admiſſion, before they had made ſuch an outcry againſt him. What not one, ſay they, what not an idolater, an inceſtuous perſon, a hater of the godly, a witch? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Why doth not Mr. <hi>H.</hi> after his urging the neceſſity of coming (and that with ſuch ſtrength of argument, as I beleeve will never be taken off by any) diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between a profane and preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous coming to an ordinance, and a Chriſtian coming in conformity to Gods worſhip? and he ſaith, Though it be better not to come, then to come in a profane way (that being rebellion and ſin in the fact) yet it is better to come in a Chriſtian way, though but in an outward conformity to Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, then altogether to neglect it: the which being granted, and practiſed of all, in all other duties; he thinks it but a begging of the queſtion to deny it in the Sacrament, pag. 73, 74.</p>
            <p>I profeſſe the Gentlemen in their
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:42522:88"/>anſwer to what Mr. <hi>H.</hi> hath written, in three or four pages together, have done nothing but trifle; as if they were glad they could but ſhift their hands of what is urged againſt them, miſerably begging the queſtion in every thing they aſſert. But pag. 147. they aske if thoſe do not come in a profane way, that come but in an outward conformity; and whether the moſt profane wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches do not ſo come, and think they have done enough: and they urge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places of Scripture againſt this, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.11. &amp; 66.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. &amp; 7. chap. from whence they inferre that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction is abhorred of the Lord; and that whoſoever comes in an outward conformity only, comes in a preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous and profane way.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that notwithſtanding theſe Scriptures, Mr. <hi>Humſreys</hi> poſition is ſtill a truth; namely, that it is better to come in a Chriſtian way (though but in outward conformity to Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice) then altogether to neglect it: For (as he ſaith) it is confeſſed by all in all other duties, &amp; therefore it is but a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the queſtion to deny it in this.</p>
            <p>And beſides, theſe Scriptures do no
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:42522:88"/>more reſpect the Paſſeover then all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of Gods worſhip and ſervice. And I beleeve theſe Gentlemen will not deny but in other duties of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as prayer, hearing the Word, and ſinging of Pſalmes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> externall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity is better and not ſo abhorred of the Lord who commands theſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as wholly to neglect them.</p>
            <p>But they ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> whoſoever comes in a meer outward conformity, comes in a preſumptuous and profane way.</p>
            <p>Gods commands free ſuch comers from preſumption and profaneneſſe in that particular;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
               </label> as to the matter of obedience: and I know nothing in all the holy Scripture againſt this; but doubtleſſe the want of outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity unto the Lawes of God is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted rebellion, and that which the Lord alwaies complained of in Iſrael of old, and puniſhed them for too. And they had many promiſes and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements unto externall obedience: and it never went ill with them ſo long as they outwardly conformed to Gods own appointments; nay we know wicked men have been rewarded for outward obedience to the word of the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:42522:89"/>
            <p>For that firſt of <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> the ſcope of the chapter is to demonſtrate and ſhew what a moſt horrible apoſtaſie there was of the whole people of <hi>Judah</hi> at that time, but eſpecially of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and judges over them, verſ. 21, 22, 23. in ſo much that verſ. 10. they are called rulers of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and princes of <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> becauſe they were ſo dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate from what they ſhould be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to divine appointment: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no wonder if the Lord do upbraid them with their ſacrifices, new moons, ſabbaths, and ſolemn meetings; and that the Lord regarded them not; why? their hands were full of oppreſſion and bloud; there was no anſwerableneſſe in other things to the duties of worſhip they did perform: and yet they thought becauſe they had the worſhip of God amongſt them, they might do all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of abominations; and that was the uſe they made of former deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And yet it is hard to ſay that they had been leſſe ſinfull if they had alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether omitted the duties of worſhip, or that they were condemned becauſe they did perform them. The Lord tels them, that if they would put away the evill
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:42522:89"/>of their doings, and ceaſe to do evill and learn to do well; ſeek judgement, relieve the oppreſſed, judge the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, plead the cauſe of the widow (the which things they might do) then the Lord promiſes grace and favour, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin, and acceptance in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: but the want of obedience in thoſe particulars, made them not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted in the things of Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded worſhip: yet they might not leave off the worſhip of God; neither is here any thing to affright them from it, but motives and argument uſed to make them more obedient in all other obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances anſwerable to that worſhip of God, as they expected good from him.</p>
            <p>Now what is all this to them that yeeld an outward conformity (at leaſt) in all or moſt things which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, to prove that it is no better for them to perform duties of worſhip then to omit them altogether; or that it is better for all unregenerate perſons not to come to the Sacrament, then to come in a Chriſtian way, though but in outward conformity only, which is the main thing now in queſtion.</p>
            <p>And the like may be ſaid of that
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:42522:90"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:42522:90"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:42522:91"/>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.3. <hi>He that killeth an oxe, is as if he ſlew a man, and he that ſacrificeth a lambe, as if he cut off a dogs neck,</hi> &amp;c. What is the reaſon of all this? <hi>Becauſe they have choſen their own waies, and their ſoul delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in their own abominations; therefore the Lord will alſo chuſe their deluſions, and bring their fears upon them,</hi> &amp;c. verſ. 3.4. The truth is, the fault lay not in doing thoſe things, but in not doing all that the Lord required as well as they could; but they would do ſome things he commanded, and other things of their own chuſing, even their own abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, like thoſe ſpoken of <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. that cry, The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord; and yet will ſteal, murder, and commit adultery, and ſwear falſly, and burn incenſe to Baal, and walk after other gods; and come and ſtand before God in his houſe; and ſay, We are delivered to commit all theſe abominations. This is a profane pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous coming to an ordinance of God; but to come in a Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity unto duties of worſhip, in hope of a bleſſing; being reſtrained from ſuch enormities as are ſpoken of in theſe Scriptures, is a different thing;
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:42522:91"/>eſpecially theſe places reſpecting natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſins rather then of particular pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons.</p>
            <p>But theſe Gentlemen judge, that this outward conſormity in the duties of Chriſtianity, according to the preſent capacity of perſons in the Church, as they are able to performe, is a ſweet bit for the Devill, and a means to keep up rotten formality ſtill.</p>
            <p>But I pray you, what is reformation in the Church, but to bring people to yeeld an outward conformity to the clear and undiſputable Lawes which Jeſus Chriſt hath ſet up in the Church? I wiſh with all my heart, the generality of Chriſts ſubjects in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> were reduced to that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though but meerly externall. I ſhould then think we were very hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; and ſhould much rejoice to ſee ſuch daies and times in <hi>England:</hi> and I muſt confeſſe my deſires and prayers unto the Lord are, that all our exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitances may be reduced unto unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Chriſtian obedience (though it were but in reſpect of the outward man) in doctrine, worſhip and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: that all might come under the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:42522:92"/>ordinary means and waies of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: and that we might teach our poſterity in the way of holy profeſſion and eſtabliſhment of the true and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oracles of God, in reſpect of which for the preſent, we are the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy of all the reformed Churches in Chriſtendome. For ſome men cannot indure to hear of ſuch words as uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in Religion, under the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of Chriſtian Lawes of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; nor of a form of godlineſſe, and holy order in the Church of Chriſt: but in the Kingdome of Chriſt would (upon the matter) have every one left to his liberty, to do what ſeems good in his own eyes. But our God is the God of order, and not of confuſion. And I doubt not but the Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate hath as much power to reform Religion in times of defection and apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie, according to the manifeſt Lawes of Jeſus Chriſt by whom they rule, as the Kings and rulers of the houſe of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> had; and ought to follow thoſe glorious preſidents, <hi>Joſiah, Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> who were carefull to reform Religion in all things according to the known Lawes of God: Theſe examples
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:42522:92"/>are recorded for our learning, and for the incouragement of thoſe whoſe hearts are warmed with the love of God, and zeal for his glory, to improve the advantages of power and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to bring both Miniſters and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to a conformity in the externals of holy worſhip and order. And the memory of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is bleſſed, becauſe of her care to reftrain the Papiſts from their ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and cruelty, and to draw on the whole people of the Nation to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion: And the ſucceſſe of this her care in reforming and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the true Religion, hath been very glorious in all reformed Churches abroad; and indeed was inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of the greateſt bleſſing that ever this nation was poſſeſſed of: for being put into a peaceable injoyment of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ordinances and godly order; we are ſtill (by that means) a people in Covenant, and have the Lord for our God, yet not without our fears, leſt the lukewarmneſſe of all in the things of our God, eſpecially in the matters of his worſhip, will in a ſhort time dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all our glory, and render us a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:42522:93"/>moſt deſpicable and odious to God and men, if not utterly unchurch and diſcovenant us, as ſome do ſlanderouſly report that we are already.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall now come to the third thing propounded, namely, that all in the Church, and of years, ought to ſubmit themſelves to the diſcipline of the Church, not to be denyed any externall Church priviledge untill they be judicially proceeded againſt, and juſtly excommunicated. To omit what hath been already ſaid in anſwer to the Doctor touching excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I ſhall propoſe ſome few things further to be conſidered for the ſtating and clearing of the true diſcipline: and then I ſhall examine whether that which theſe Gentlemen commend to their reader, be any thing like the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline of Chriſt held forth in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and practiſed by the primitive Churches of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That all that are baptized and of years, muſt of neceſſity come under the obligation of all the Lawes and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, of which Diſcipline is one, and therefore none may plead ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from it: whoſoever he be that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:42522:93"/>is a brother and within, comes under the Church judgement and cenſure, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That although all ought to come under the diſcipline of that Church of which they are members, yet may not any be denied Church priviledges for the ſtate of unregeneracy meerly, nor for barrenneſſe and unfruitfulneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ordinary means of grace; or not coming up to the practiſe of ſuch duties as are private, and more doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then the duties of publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are. For it is certain that Jeſus Chriſt hath his elect ones, loſt ſheep, and children of God among the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſeed of Chriſtians, or to come of them, as he had among the Jewes: and theſe elect ones he is pleaſed more ſavingly to call, ſome at the third hour, others not untill the eleventh hour of the day of grace vouchſafed to them. And theſe being the ſpeciall objects of redemption, included in the Goſpell Covenant, to whom the promiſes of the firſt grace do properly belong; we muſt ſuffer Jeſus Chriſt to have the liberty of his own appointments in the Church; as the only means of gathering in ſuch
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:42522:94"/>unto himſelf; that they may have life in him, and live unto him according to the grace they have received from him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the ſcandalous in the Church are to be dealt with under the notion of offending brethren, whom they that are ſpirituall ought by private admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, and Chriſtian counſell, and wiſe and ſeaſonable reproofs, to reſtore in the ſpirit of meekneſſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. And the perſon or ſin of any member not to be nominated in publick, while there is any reaſonable hope (in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) of amendment by the private means: provided the offence be not already publick and infamous to all; in that caſe, I think, though the offender be penitent and aſhamed, yet he ought to be rebuked before all that the reſt may fear, and the congregation be ſatisfied. And that it is only in caſe of obſtinacy, and hating to be reformed, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all poſſible means uſed by the Church for their reformation, that the authoritative act of excommunication is to be iſſued out againſt any member. The Apoſtle did more often threaten and ſhake the rod then make uſe of it.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:42522:94"/>The adminiſtration of publick cenſures ſhould be carried on with that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnneſs and mourning over the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that might ſhew a reall unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to put the ſame in execution; if any other means would humble and break the heart of an obſtinate tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor. And though there may be in the Church a readineſſe to revenge all wilfull diſobedience, yet a readineſſe to forgive alſo, as they ſhall ſee cauſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That none ought to uſurpe the power of the keyes of Chriſts viſible Kingdome, or take upon them the power of ſtewards, and to be Judges of Chriſts ſubjects, that have not a clear warrant in the Word for the ſame, leſt they be judged. For my part, I muſt confeſſe, I utterly reject as impious and againſt all rule and order for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon members to claim an intereſt in the exerciſe of the keys, either of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Sacraments or Diſcipline, ſave only to be obedient in declining fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity with thoſe that are juſtly excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, and all communion with them in worſhip: and to be witneſſes to atteſt what they know againſt an offending brother, when it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:42522:95"/>to prove the fact and conviction of his obſtinacy. I profeſſe I wonder that any acquainted with the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures ſhould plead for any other pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be allowed to any of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon members: I cannot ſee how this ſhould be, but that ſome men drive on deſignes of their own factious framing, rather to hinder the ſetting up of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, then any way to advance it. What diſmall diviſions, ſeparations and confuſions, what prejudices, heart-burnings and bitterneſſe do ſuch pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes every where neceſſarily occaſion between Paſtours and their people? while the better part muſt withdraw from the reſt, and ſet up Diſcipline among themſelves; chuſe their own officers, and uſe a language beyond the ordinary, and think they are in a fine poſture: when (alaſſe) they are out of their ſtation, and all they do is but erecting waies of their own chuſing, and ſetting up altars to ſin; ſome of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> craft to keep the people from worſhipping at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And the truth is, members that ſeparate from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy are not like to live long. What ſtrange exorbitances very often are the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:42522:95"/>conſequences of ſuch uncharitable zealous waies? And how can it be avoided, if the power of the keys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide in the common brotherhood, but the major part of a parochiall congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation may chuſe their own officers, ſet up Diſcipline, and judge in the Church? and what reformation is then like to follow, may eaſily be imagined. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe all Church members, as ſuch, ſtand upon a levell in point of externall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges: for we do not finde different priviledges of thoſe that are members of the ſame Church, planted together into the ſame viſible body by baptiſm: and ſo by conſequence women and children, ignorant and ſcandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall have power to judge the reſt; nay they may create and ordain their own officers, and conſequently take upon them all Goſpell adminiſtrations: for if the keys reſide in them original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo that they may make Miniſters <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then they themſelves are much more ſuch, and may do the works they are to do. The effect cannot be greater then the cauſe.</p>
            <p>But they will ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> the power of the keys reſides not in all, but in worthy
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:42522:96"/>and compleat Church-members, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers that have the ſpirit of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know no ſuch diſtinction in the Word of God.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Look upon the Church of the Jewes; they were a holy nation, a kingdome of Prieſts, a peculiar and royall people in generall without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of worthy and unworthy, compleat and incompleat. And doth not the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> uſe the ſame words and apply them to the ſcattered ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers embracing Chriſtianity? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. And doth not the Apoſtle give equall titles to all thoſe to whom he writes, and to all in every place that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the name of the Lord Jeſus? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. If we never read of any ſuch diſtinction in <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets; nor finde any ſuch uſed by Chriſt or his Apoſtles, why ſhould any plead for it in our congregations, but that they would ſee more then all that ever were before them?</p>
            <p>But the keyes were given to the twelve as beleevers,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> and that which is given to them as ſuch, is given to the whole kinde of beleevers in the world.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solut. </seg>
               </label> 
            </p>
            <p>That the twelve were impowered with
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:42522:96"/>the keyes of Chriſts Kingdom, is beyond all diſpute, and that they were beleevers when they received that power, is as certain: but that the Lord Jeſus gave the keyes to them as ſuch, is denyed. And they might as well ſay, they were given to them as men; for they were men when they received them. But the truth is, that though there were many Diſciples and beleevers beſide the twelve; yet of his meer good pleaſure, he gave the keyes of his Kingdome to the twelve only, not to the reſt that beleeved as well as they. He hath ſet ſome in the Church, Apoſtles, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours and Teachers, not all. And we know the twelve, by vertue of that authority received, preached and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and ordered all the affairs of Chriſts Kingdome, during their age: they planted ſeverall Churches, and ordained them Elders and Deacons; they were the inſtruments for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the Goſpell in almoſt all places. Doubtleſſe after Jeſus Chriſt had received all power in heaven and earth, he put the twelve only in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to build his Church; and they ordained Elders and Deacons, and gave
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:42522:97"/>order to ſome others, as <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> to ordain; and directed them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to commit the ſame power to able and ſit men, in after ages to teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> the Angell of every Church is writ unto, and blamed or commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded according as they demeaned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their places, in oppoſing er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour or cleaving to the truth. But we never finde that the common brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood or memberſhip were impowered with the keys, either by Chriſt or by his Apoſtles, or any that drived authority immediately from them: and therefore they have it not at all: and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude themſelves, and aſſume unto themſelves things of ſuch an high na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is a moſt inſolent boldneſſe; and they may fear to periſh in the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying of <hi>Corah</hi> and his company.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I cannot conceive how there ſhould be any true diſcipline practiſed in our Churches without the ſpeciall aſſiſtance, countenance and power of the civill Magiſtrate, as the ſtate of things are in <hi>England:</hi> For almoſt all of all ſorts, are either careleſſe, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient, or erroneous, and not willing
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:42522:97"/>to come under diſcipline. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though theſe Gentlemen ſay it is our own fault; and why do we not ſet upon it, beginning with the minor part? yet this is very ill, nay abſurdly advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. For as I ſaid before, I beleeve I ſhall never ſee true diſcipline exerciſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> untill the Lord ſo move upon the hearts of our Rulers, as to make them inſtrumentall to put the Church into that capacity: which ordinarily cannot be without a nationall aſſembly of learned, grave, moderate and godly Divines; choſen (if poſſible) by the whole; and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on without tumult. And that a profeſſion of faith (if not already done) may be ſo clearly drawn up in reſpect of fundamentals in doctrine and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, according to evident rules of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, as may be eſtabliſhed to be the publique profeſſion of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which all whatſoever ſhould with peaceable ſpirits ſubmit unto. And alſo that the ſubjects of the keyes in a nationall Church may be more clearly determined, and liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience better ſtated and bounded; that the reformation of the whole may grow
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:42522:98"/>up together, at leaſt in all the externals of Chriſtian obedience. Otherwiſe how ſhall diſcipline be practiſed, if carnall and looſe Chriſtians ſhall be left at liberty, whether they will come under it or no? Now I ſay, while they are within the viſible Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our Lord Jeſus, and profeſſe his Name in hope of eternall life, why ſhould they not ſubmit to all his Lawes, as the way and means appointed of that bleſſed end? And the ſame grounds that do warrant the reſtraining offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from evill, and the forcing of them to do their duty in reference to ſome of the Lawes of Chriſt, do warrant the doing of the like in reference to all the reſt of his royall Lawes. What is more ſutable, then that they that reign and rule only by Jeſus Chriſt, ſhould put forth their power, and improve all their intereſt for the advancing of Chriſts Scepter over all?</p>
            <p>I confeſſe theſe Gentlemen have ſome unhappy expreſſions, queſtioning our Church members; becauſe (as they ſay) the main inſtruments of bringing them to the true Religion in <hi>England,</hi> were ſuch as carryed it on by a civill
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:42522:98"/>power; when the outward calling ought to be by the word only, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the moſt of our common people never had, they ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. I wiſh our Governours had that holy and grounded zeal for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of what is amiſſe now in the Church, that our firſt reformers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in point of reformation in their generation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt diſtinguiſh of a twofold ſtate of Church memberſhip, or the way of bringing people to be Church members, 1. Aliens of years are to be diſcipled and called by the Word before they may be baptized and received into the Church: and ſo it was in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles firſt planting of Churches. But 2. The ſeed of perſons ſo called are by vertue of the Goſpell Covenant mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers borne; and upon that account are baptized: and when they come to years are as much under the obligation of all holy obſervances, as thoſe that are called by the word: So it was in the Church of the Jewes in reſpect of all that were circumciſed: ſo that Church memberſhip is and may be pleaded from birth priviledge, Gal. 2.15. <hi>We who are Jewes by nature, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Our firſt reformers did not force
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:42522:99"/>Heathens to receive and profeſſe the Proteſtant Religion; but reduced bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized erring Chriſtians unto that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and reformation which their Baptiſme and profeſſion did oblige and ingage them unto: according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of godly Kings and Prophets amongſt the Jewes, in caſe of defection and irregularity. I might produce di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers inſtances of this holy and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous care and zeal in reforming; but thoſe that are acquainted with the Scripture can remember the hiſtories of them. And orthodox Divines do gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally hold, that the Baptiſme of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt is valid,, and need not be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And it need not be doubted, but upon that ground, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> or the <hi>French</hi> King, if the Lord ſhould give them a heart throughly convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of, and affected with the truth, might reduce their ſubjects (if they were able) to that conformity to the Lawes of Jeſus Chriſt which their Baptiſme doth oblige them to. <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf upon ſuch a reformation, might become a true viſible Church, without any repeating either of the ordination of their Miniſters, or their Baptiſme.
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:42522:99"/>Were all that ſuperfluity of naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, from time to time contracted, in Doctrine, worſhip and diſcipline purged out; and all adminiſtrations made conformable to the Lawes of Jeſus Chriſt (as it was with them for ſome hundreds of years from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times) we could not tell what to object againſt them, but might have communion with them. Say that we heretofore were a member of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived all ſacred ordinances from them; having now repented of the evils and abominations which the holy things of Chriſt were polluted with, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them according to the inſtitution; what can be objected againſt us, though we were put in poſſeſſion of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt by means of the civill power?</p>
            <p n="4">4. If an argument drawn from ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe be of any force in any caſe, ſurely in ſupernaturall and ſpirituall events above any other: and we are not left without innumerable evidences of the divine operations upon the ſouls of many in our Nation, through the bleſſing of the Lord upon the uſe of thoſe holy adminiſtrations of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:42522:100"/>which our firſt reformers with zeal, care and power brought our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers under; bleſſed be God for this unſpeakable gift.</p>
            <p>This for the fifth thing propoſed concerning diſcipline.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſixth and laſt is this, That ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcipline is ſo to be ordered, that the edification of all may be beſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and preſerved, and the objects of Church cenſures may be healed rather then hurt by them. Sometimes the Church muſt rebuke ſome, that the reſt may fear; and ſentence ſome few, moſt notorious offenders, when many deſerve the ſame puniſhment, rather then indanger the peace, union and edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church; puniſh and chaſtiſe what they can, with the health and ſafety of the whole: and with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bear and forbear, when the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is like to prove worſe then the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. Lawfull things are not alwaies expedient, nor conſiſt with charity.</p>
            <p>It is a good ſaying of <hi>Cyprian</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by <hi>Calvin, Let the Church merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly correct what they can, and what they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, let them patiently ſuffer, and with love groan and lament it:</hi> And to the ſame
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:42522:100"/>purpoſe he brings in the advice of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> touching the abounding of drunkenneſſe in <hi>Africa;</hi> this and the like evils (according to his judgement) are to be taken away, not roughly, nor after an imperious manner; but more by teaching then commanding; more by admoniſhing then by threatning; and that is the way to deal with a multitude of ſinners; ſeverity muſt be exerciſed on the ſin of a few, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And he concludeth thus; The command of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. to caſt out the wicked, is in no caſe to be neglected, when it may be done without perill of breaking the peace of the Church, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>Sect.</hi> 11.13.</p>
            <p>And we may take notice, that where there is mention made of the Apoſtles exerciſing of Diſcipline, it is only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on particular perſons, and not upon a multitude: when he findes many guilty of evill practiſes, he reproves, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes, and threatens to come with the rod, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.20. &amp; 13.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.21.</p>
            <p>And truly, as the ſtate of things now ſtands, I think it will be found a very difficult thing to get into poſſeſſion of the true way of diſcipline, and to make
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:42522:101"/>that uſe of it, that the Churches peace and edification may be promoted and not prejudiced by it. For either the ſuppoſed unregenerate in the Church ſhall (on the one hand) be caſt off and ſeparated from, as in the Independent way and ſome others; or elſe (on the other hand) the diſſenting brethren will be judged ſchiſmatical, for cauſing diviſions and ſeparations in the Church, contrary to the Doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt. And therefore our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is the more ſad, in that Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline which tends ſo much to the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being of the Church can ſo hardly be attained amongſt us. Thus I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you my judgement and apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this point.</p>
            <p>Now in the next place, Becauſe theſe Gentlemen have commended a way of Diſcipline to the godly, I ſhall crave leave a little to examine it; whether it be ſuch a one as godly men may ſafely receive and uſe as the diſcipline of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; and not rather reject it, as having nothing of Chriſt in the riſe and root of it, according to holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: and this I ſhall do very briefly, becauſe I have ſaid ſo much to the point already.</p>
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:42522:101"/>
            <p n="1">1. It's well they acknowledge our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiall congregations to be true Churches, though it be but in a large ſenſe: for being ſuch, they come under the ſame lawes and priviledges exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, which belong to true Churches in the ſtricteſt ſenſe; that is, unleſſe they can finde a different rule in Scripture for true Churches, though not in the ſame degree of purity; which I believe they cannot, becauſe I do not finde but <hi>Laodicea</hi> and <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> as they were both true Churches, ſo they were both under the ſame rule, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They confeſſe that none but ſuch as are already excommunicated, and ſuch as ought to be excommunicated, are to be kept from the Sacrament: and in this Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and they ſeem to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, pag. 27. provided (ſay they) that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> mean ſuch as of right ought to be excommunicated by the Church. For his meaning, they may be ſure he doth not mean that Church members ſhould be cenſured without regular tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and that by a Church that is in a fit capacity to hear and judge, and ſentence according to divine rule. But how will theſe gentlemen prove that
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:42522:102"/>the greater part in a pariſh are ſuch as of right ought to be excommunicated, and never put it to the triall, whether their ſinfulneſſe be of that nature, for which excommunication may and ought to be inflicted? It is obſtinacy and wilfull perſiſting in groſſe ſins, after private and publick admonition, that is to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with excommunication; and how can they know that the greater part of a pariſh do ſo ſin, when they never admoniſh them, either privately or publickly? Sure there muſt be a clear conviction of their ſins, and all fair and amicable Chriſtian means uſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim them, before they can judge any in their pariſh excommunicable; were they in a capacity thus authoritatively to deal with them, which I think they are not.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But they ſay, <hi>This is a moſt generally received truth, that every particular congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation hath power in it ſelf to reforme it ſelf, according to what ſhall be practicable to them,</hi> pag. 158. To which I ſhall oppoſe their own words, pag. 7.10. Where firſt they ſay, <hi>That the ignorant and profane muſt be withdrawn from, becauſe it is clear, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be regularly caſt out by diſcipline, neither
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:42522:102"/>is there any way how they ſhould be rightly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated; for that the major part of the Church is corrupt; and the ſame may be well ſuppoſed of moſt of the mixt parochiall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations in</hi> England: <hi>and will not excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, nor are fit to do ſo, nor to chuſe officers to do it,</hi> pag. 9, 10.</p>
            <p>Now is not this a ſtrange thing? they condemn Mr. <hi>Humfrey</hi> for not ſetting up Diſcipline in his Church: and ſtrongly aſſert, <hi>That every Congregation hath power to reform it ſelf, and yet they ſay it is clear, that the ignorant and profane cannot be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly caſt out by Diſcipline, nor is there any way how they ſhould be rightly excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated.</hi> Reader, Canſt thou deſire a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter juſtification of Mr. <hi>Humfreys</hi> preſent practiſe in the matter of the Sacrament, then theſe mens own words? If he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reform in a right way, muſt he and others undergoe reproach, becauſe they dare not exerciſe diſcipline in a wrong way, as theſe gentlemen do? There are many ſober and godly Miniſters that judge it better not to pretend to diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline at all; then to take up that way to which ſome give the name, when there is nothing of the nature of true diſcipline. If we cannot exerciſe
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:42522:103"/>it aright, why ſhould any be cenſured for not exerciſing it wrong? To doe evill that good may come, the Apoſtle judges damnable: ſo rarely it is that good ends and evill means ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>But they ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>If they cannot regularly excommunicate the ignorant and ſcandalous that are excommunicable, then the Miniſter and thoſe that are convinced of their duty to come up to a more cloſe communion and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Goſpell, muſt withdraw from the corrupt majority; and wait for their coming in upon the ſame termes agreed upon by the minor part;</hi> and for this they commend to us <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> It is very harſh to ſay, that the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in the Church are for that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable; they may expreſſe their deſires to learn, and uſe the means ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to that end; and ſo not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable, nor to be ſeparated from. And for the ſcandalous, they are to be tryed, as was hinted before, and then excommunicated if there be juſt cauſe: elſe they ſhall be deprived of a ſpeciall ordinance of the Church, intended as the laſt remedy to convert the obſtinate ſinner from his evill
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:42522:103"/>waies: And as it is a means of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion (as theſe Gentlemen do confeſs) the Magiſtrate may conſtrain all in the Church to come under it, and ſubmit to it.</p>
            <p>They ſay, <hi>Ieſus Christ ſhould rule by the Word of his mouth, and not by the Magiſtrates compelling edicts:</hi> and yet they ſay, <hi>That in bringing all to converting ordinances (they humbly conceive) the Magiſtrate is to put forth his power,</hi> pag. 176. And then will it not hence follow, that as diſcipline is a means of converſion, the Magiſtrate is to put forth his power for the bringing of all under it. Yea, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and to aſſiſt the Church in the ſetling, exerciſe and execution of it. And to withdraw without a judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all proceeding, neither doth nor can attain the true end; but doth har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and prejudice ſinners a great deal more, and ſo makes them worſe in ſtead of making them better. The end of withdrawing (according to the Scripture) is to bring the perſons withdrawn from, to ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and is this a likely way to attain that end, for a Miniſter and ſome ten or twenty of his people, to
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:42522:104"/>withdraw from three or four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred (as in ſome places would be the caſe) they all profeſſing the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? Do theſe men think the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle meant ſuch a withdrawing, to bring ſinners in the Church to ſhame? The rule is in reference to a diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly brother to bring him to ſhame; but in our times applyed to hundreds at once, by the minor part in a Church; and that very unfitly too; there being many in ſome ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that as truly fear God, and live in Chriſtian obedience beyond ſome of them that withdraw from them; who yet had rather be reckoned among ſinners, then to joine with them, that by ſchiſme break the peace of the Church.</p>
            <p>Beſides, grant that many of them ſhould be excommunicable, doth that warrant a ſeparation, when it is not in our power to do it regularly? It is ten to one that thoſe that are ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for ſeparating, did never deal with their offending brethren, ſo far as they lawfully may and ought, to amend them. If we ſhould deal thus in the Kingdome of this world, as they
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:42522:104"/>do in the Kingdome of Chriſt, there would be but a ſad accompt given of many ſubjects therein. If it were enough to ſay ſuch are fellons and hangable by the Law, and thereupon never bring them to triall, but knock them on the head, and there's an end of them; How long think you would this Common-wealth ſtand, were ſuch a confuſion and barbariſme tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated?</p>
            <p>Suppoſe theſe Gentlemen in <hi>Gloceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> are run into a dangerous way of ſchiſme in the Church, through error and miſtake; would they be content (without any ordinary means uſed to convince them of their error, or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and admoniſhing them to retract) to be forthwith ſentenced by a Bench of Elders, as ſchiſmaticall perſons, and upon that accompt ſuſpended from their Miniſtry? I think they would not. And yet by what they appear by their Book to be, I think they are ſcarce qualified as Biſhops ought to be, that undertake the rule of Chriſts Flock; and my prayer is, that their uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable practiſes may not be an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of deſtroying many weak
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:42522:105"/>brethren for whom Chriſt died.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. it comes now to be examined; that we may ſee how it is appliable to theſe new found models of Diſcipline hinted at by theſe men in the preamble of their Book. And it is moſt clear and certain that the main ſcope of our Saviour is to teach us theſe two things in generall.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That the meaneſt perſon coming to Chriſt and profeſſing faith in him, is not to be deſpiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That not to deal with offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding brethren in the way and order by him there preſcribed is to deſpiſe them.</hi> And then for the way preſcribed by our Saviour, it ought to begin with pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate admonition in caſe of a brother offending, and if that prevail for his amendment, he is not to be put to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſhame: but if that will not work upon him, then upon ſufficient proof of the fact, he may and ought to be complained of to the Church, and the Church may convent him before them, admoniſh to confeſſe and reform his ſin. But if out of obſtinacy he ſtubbornly refuſe to hear the Church, after firſt and ſecond admonition, then to be caſt out, not otherwiſe.</p>
            <pb n="181" facs="tcp:42522:105"/>
            <p>Now what is there in all this to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or warrant theſe Gentlemens practiſe? do they proceed after this manner with every offending brother in their ſeverall pariſhes, before they deny them Chriſtian communion in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper? If not, why will they urge a rule from Jeſus Chriſt to others, which they themſelves will not practiſe? Would they have others do that themſelves neither will nor can do, as themſelves confeſſe, where the greater part is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt? And this being the caſe of moſt Pariſhes in <hi>England,</hi> how ſhall we take up an eſtabliſhment of diſcipline from this place? Why, they tell us, by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from the major part of the Church: But then it will be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, whether this Scripture do war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant any ſuch practiſe; and it muſt needs be granted it doth not. Thus you may ſee how ſutable theſe new models are to thoſe Scriptures alledged by themſelves for proof thereof.</p>
            <p>But to proceed a little further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. The greateſt difficulty (as I conceive) lies in the word <hi>Church,</hi> when our Saviour
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:42522:106"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:42522:106"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:42522:107"/>bids tell the Church: I ſhall give my thoughts concerning that alſo, and leave them to the intelligent reader to conſider.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I conceive our Saviours rules here given in this caſe, reſpected the preſent ſtate of the Jewes Church, as well as the Chriſtian Churches in after times; and was practicable in that preſent ſtate of the Jewes Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. According to the ſame rules and order his Diſciples and their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers ſhould act in after ages, as verſ. 18. doth plainly ſhew.</p>
            <p>Concerning the former of theſe, as the rule given by our Saviour reſpected the preſent ſtate of the Jewes, and was practicable in that Church, we are to inquire whether the complaint were to be made to the whole Church conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of rulers and ruled, aſſembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in holy worſhip; or to the Rulers and Officers of the Church on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, aſſembled in a Court of Judicature, for the hearing of complaints, and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of offenders, and puniſhing evill manners.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, That to one it ſeems very probable, that Church here
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:42522:107"/>is to be taken in the latter ſenſe: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the common people among the Jewes, never had any ſuch authority in that Church, as to judge of manners, and cenſure according to the rule gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by our Saviour in this Scripture. But it is clear that they had a Councell of Elders called the Sanhedrin, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.22. that judged of manners, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed ſuch as reviled their brother, intimated in theſe words, <hi>He that ſhall ſay to his Brother, Racha, ſhall be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Councell or Sanhedrin.</hi> The Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees and chief Prieſts were chief in that Councell, or it conſiſted wholly of them; for they undertook to caſt out of the Synagogue, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. &amp; 12. And when <hi>Saul</hi> breathed out threatnings againſt the Saints, in zeal of reducing them to the Church from which they were departed and ſeduced, as he thought, he went to the chief Prieſts and all the eſtate of the Elders for his commiſſion, and he received antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from them, to bring both men and women unto Jeruſalem to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 22.15. And that eſtate of Elders in the originall is called a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, which alſo ſhewes that it was
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:42522:108"/>made up of chief Officers of the Church called Presbyters; ſome of which were chief Prieſts, the other Phariſees, and ſome ſubordinate Presbyters were joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with them to make up that aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, having authority to judge of manners according to the Lawes of God: however upon miſtake they puniſhed the true profeſſors of the Chriſtian Religion, yet not under the notion of profeſſors of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but out of zeal to reduce the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving Jewes to conformity to the old adminiſtration, as judging it ſtill in force, as it was delivered by <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any make queſtion whether this Presbytery (according to the Text) were the Church to whom complaint was to be made concerning ſtubborn offenders, I anſwer, that Councell or Presbytery was made up of the chief Officers of the whole Church, and ſo the Church repreſentative, on whom alone all the authority of the Church was involved, for the puniſhing of ſin, and preſerving the peace of the whole. And for the word Church, they that are acquainted with the Original language, know it is uſed for any aſſembly, or
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:42522:108"/>congregation called together, whether to civill or ſacred ends; and ſo theſe Elders and Rulers of the Jewes aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled together for the ends aforeſaid are not unproperly called a Church.</p>
            <p>And for the latter thing propounded before, namely that the Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in after ages are to proceed by the ſame rule, and in the ſame order the Church of the Jewes then did, that is to ſay, by a Presbytery, ſeems to me very probable. For firſt of all there were in uſe in the Chriſtian Church, in reference to the rule and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, the ſame names that were in the Church of the Jewes, which is a ſign that there was the ſame thing. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> who was well acquainted with the nature of the Presbytery at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> from whom he received authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to trouble the beleeving Jewes, cals an aſſembly of Elders or Church officers a Presbytery, of which what better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be conceived then this, the reſemblance that was between this El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip and the great Councel in the Church of the Jewes? It is clear the Apoſtles themſelves did order all things in the Church; ordained Elders, and
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:42522:109"/>authorized them in the Name of Chriſt to ordain others, &amp;c. And they were as much Rulers and Officers over the Catholick Church, as the chief Prieſts and Elders were to the Jewes. And hence in the Apoſtolical Churches, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Miniſters was derived from them that were Officers to the whole Church; and in a moſt immediate man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by Jeſus Chriſt were conſtituted ſo to be: which makes me inclinable to beleeve, that thoſe ſtill that are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Officers for the good and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the whole, ſhould be ordained by ſuch a Presbytery that are intruſted with that power, by the Officers of the whole as much as may be. So farre am I from conſenting to theſe men that take it for granted, that the common members of a particular ſociety, may chuſe and inſtall their own officers. Now what is there in all this for that pretended way of diſcipline which theſe Gentlemen commend to their reader? here is not the leaſt warrant for any to ſeparate from the Church, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw (for all is one) nor for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to rule, and chuſe their own Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, nor for impoſing a Church Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:42522:109"/>explicitly to be profeſſed in the congregation; and thoſe that will not come up to this and ſuch like termes, muſt not be admitted unto Sacramentall communion. Nor is here any warrant for ſentencing Church members before a regular triall; nay here is no warrant for any ſingle Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to ſet up diſcipline over his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, without the conſent and conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the reverent brethren of the Miniſtry with them. The key of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline is not at all in one alone, but rather in the whole together.</p>
            <p>A word more on that Scripture, as it is directed to the Apoſtles, verſ. 18, 19, 20. and ſo in them to the officers of the Church in ſucceeding ages to the end of the world. <hi>Verily</hi> (ſaith our Saviour there) <hi>if two of you ſhall agree on earth as touching any thing that they ſhall aske, it ſhall be done for them of my Father which is in heaven: for where two or three are gathered together in my Name, there am I in the midſt of them.</hi> Theſe words ſeem to have reference unto what was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before concerning the authority of the Jewes Church Officers; and our Saviour would have his Apoſtles to
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:42522:110"/>know, that though their authority may ſeem to the world, yea, and to themſelves to be weak and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in reſpect of that great bench of Elders, generally ſubmitted unto by the Jewes, yet they ſhould have as great authority to binde and looſe as the other; nay two of them by the authority given them by the Lord of the Church, ſhould be equivalent to their great authority: And we know it came ſo to paſſe. They had power to work miracles, and were inſpired with an extraordinary ſpirit; and had ſome ſpeciall promiſes peculiar to them alone, as well as gifts. They had power to give the holy Ghoſt by impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands; and an extraordinary power in prayer, and power to puniſh and kill the bodies of men for ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and hypocriſie. And we know the very Church it ſelf is ſaid to be built upon the foundation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf being the chief corner-ſtone. Now what is this to theſe Miniſters in <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter-ſhire?</hi> Dare two or three of them aſſume this power (for I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all the Miniſters of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:42522:110"/>are not of their minde and way) to do as the Apoſtles did? Suppoſe they be Miniſters of the Goſpell, is the Church built upon them, or their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? Where have they any ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that they ſhall not erre; and whatſoever they ſhall agree to aske, ſhall be done for them of the Father of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt? They plead their ſerious and ſolemn ſeeking of God; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto us their model of Diſcipline, as the reſult of their ſerious debates, and returns of their prayers: but that authority will not ſatisfie judicious Chriſtians, when the thing it ſelf is ſo inconſiſtent with the generall rules of the Word, as hath been ſhewed. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it is well known, that in many places the Miniſters of the Goſpell have uſed the like means in behalf of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their people, yet but few have run into their waies, but either fall into ſome aſſociation of Churches and Presbyteries, framing ſuch expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, as (in a manner) bring in all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a capacity of Sacramentall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and diſcipline, as in <hi>Worceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> and other places; or elſe carry on the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:42522:111"/>of their office as well as they can without Diſcipline; as being convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of their incapacity for the preſent ſo attain unto the true end and exerciſe thereof, notwithſtanding all their ſearch, diſquiſition, and indevours to ſatisfie one another therein. And the ſerious debates and ſeeking of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this, ſhould move to own and aſſent to what is concluded thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I conceive it more ſafe to adhere to the greater part of ſober Divines that have been ſerious in the uſe of theſe and all other means, to ſatisfie themſelves and others, as well as thoſe men, and yet dare not in the leaſt degree counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance their way and practiſe. I would aske them this queſtion, whether they did ever read of any ſuch practiſe, that a few particular Miniſters, by their own authority, have had the boldneſſe to withdraw from the greateſt part of their flocks, and ſet up a way of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of their own framing? and upon the matter unchurch the greateſt part of their congregations, allowing them no other priviledge in the Church, then they would to Pagans. Did the Apoſtles ever make ſo bold with any
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:42522:111"/>Chriſtian congregation that adhered to the Goſpell adminiſtrations? or did they ever authorize ordinary Presbyters to do ſo? Nay, did any ordinary Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter in the Apoſtles time, exerciſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline but upon the command of the Apoſtles? or do we finde them any where blamed becauſe they did not do it? I verily beleeve theſe Gentlemen may not aſſume ſuch an intereſt in the exerciſe of the Key of Diſcipline as the Apoſtles had, and yet they are more bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with the rod then ever any of the Apoſtles were. Alas! it's pity ſome care is not taken to reſtrain their impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious uſurpation over their ſeverall flocks. I think, ſince the ceaſing of the Apoſtles office, it is more ſutable to the Scripture alledged, and other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to elect ſuch Presbyteries to judge of manners in the Church, as were conſtituted in the Church of the Jewes, which our Saviour approved of; which yet would come ſhort of being equall with the Apoſtles, in reſpect of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which they had in the Church of Chriſt; though they were in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces men of the beſt qualifications for Rule, that any attain to in our times;
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:42522:112"/>and ſo I have done with that Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>I will trouble the reader but with two or three paſſages more about their new modell: for I have a good minde to draw to an end; and my other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions will not permit me to do much in theſe waies. Pag. 4. they tell us of the drawing up a profeſſion of faith, wherein they acknowledge their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Abominations in worſhip, profeſſing their repentance before the Lord for them.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which I ſay, It is a ſtrange ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Chriſtians, except they were ſuch as came newly out of Paganiſme, or Popery at leaſt. What abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of worſhip have been eſtabliſhed or practiſed in our Church ſince the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of it? Is it not ſtrange that the Miniſters of the Church, who ſhould be ready to defend the Church from the wicked ſlanders and reproaches of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts and other Separatiſts, ſhould thus publickly join with them, and that in ſuch a publick way before the world too? How many powerfull and ſucceſſefull Miniſters of the Goſpell, now with Jeſus Chriſt in glory, have juſtified all the ordinary parts of Gods
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:42522:112"/>worſhip, as it was practiſed in our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick aſſemblies all along, and conformed thereunto chearfully in reſpect of the ſubſtance of our worſhip? Indeed there were ſome needleſſe ceremonies uſed about worſhip, which were declared by the Church to be no part of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: now theſe were born as burthens which many of the godly deſired to be eaſed of by their removall; but it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came into their thoughts, that they were guilty of abominations in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip becauſe of them. How doth Mr. <hi>Hilderſham</hi> in his Lectures upon <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. juſtifie the Church of <hi>England</hi> as a true Church, and the ſeverall parts of worſhip practiſed therein, as being according to the inſtitution of the Lord? And how doth he from thence blame thoſe that ſeparated, or neglected the publick prayers of the Church; and yet himſelf was one of the old non-conformiſts? And Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> that went into new <hi>England,</hi> writing an Epiſtle to that Book, doth therein highly commend the Author for many things; but in a ſpeciall manner for confuting the ſeparations of the Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts: and he repeats what another re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:42522:113"/>of him, ſtyling him the hammer of Schiſmaticks, commonly called Browniſts.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Gentlemen talk of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant eſtabliſhed in Chriſt, into which they require a profeſſion to enter, of thoſe they admit to partake of the Seal of that Covenant, pag. 10.</p>
            <p>Concerning this, I ſay it were well if they would act according to their own words: for 'tis certain all Church communion is ſounded upon covenant relation; And thoſe (whoſe admittance to the Sacrament we plead for) are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have entred Covenant relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, either in their parents, or in their own perſonall profeſſion of the true Religion that holy Scriptures teach, or both, and their voluntary adhering to the adminiſtrations of the Covenant, doth atteſt their entring the Covenant, and their continuing and abiding in that relation; let them ſay what they can to the contrary.</p>
            <p>But they ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Perſons that have entred Covenant, may back-ſlide and ſo that relation ceaſe,</hi> (and they inſtance in <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi>) <hi>but thoſe that brake bread were ſuch as continued in the Apoſtles doctrin,</hi> Act. 2.42
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:42522:113"/>
               <hi>And back-ſliders are not to be admitted to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> How do they know that <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> fell off rom the Chriſtian profeſſion, when the laſt we read concerning him, is his retracting his erroneous the uphts, deſiring the Apoſtle to pray for him, that none of thoſe evils might come upon him?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſe he did backſlide and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his Baptiſme and profeſſion, would he then have deſired Chriſtian communion in the Ordinances of Chriſt? what more abſurd?</p>
            <p n="3">3. We only plead for ſuch to break bread, that continue in the Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; which we ſay all do, that adhere to the adminiſtrations of Jeſus Chriſt, ſet up in his Church, as the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry means of obtaining Covenant grace.</p>
            <p>And for what they ſay concerning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of our Covenant with God after defection from him, we heartily allow of it; provided it be done according to the Scripture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12, <hi>&amp;c. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem.</hi> 10.29. Where in the perſons of the chief, the whole ingaged to walk in all the waies of the Lord; and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and do all his commandements,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:42522:114"/>and his judgement, and his ſtatutes. This is contrary to theſe men, that would ſet up a Rail to hinder Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans from obſerving all Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; nay rather to uncovenant a people in Covenant, then ingage them to renew Covenant, and walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy their Covenant relation, in their obſervance of all covenant Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in hope of bleſſing. And I wiſh, that if the Church cannot, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate would take down the high places, that hinder the Lords people from wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping at the only place of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. If ſome have liberty to worſhip at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> why ſhould any be reſtrained from worſhipping at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and doing their homage and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in remembrance of Chriſt who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ſinners?</p>
            <p>I had thought to have added a word concerning the fourth and laſt thing propoſed in the beginning of this Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; as it was urged by Mr. <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey;</hi> namely, that Miniſters ought to do their duties as they are Miniſters, though Diſcipline be wanting; and cannot well be attained as things ſtand: of which duties, the adminiſtration of
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:42522:114"/>the Sacrament is one, which by their office they are bound to performe; as they will anſwer the neglect thereof to Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, who commands the obſervance of all his holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances in the Church, for the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his flock: And thoſe that love him will make conſcience in their places, to be faithfull to him that hath appointed them. But I fear I have been too tedious already. And Mr. <hi>Humfrey</hi> in his Rejoynder to Doctor <hi>Drake</hi> hath abundantly given ſatisfaction in the vindication of this and other truths aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in his former Book: And if he ſhall think theſe Gentlemen worthy of any further anſwer; I ſhall rather leave it to himſelf, then do any thing that may hinder the Church of God of the faithfull and profitable labours of him or any others.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:42522:115"/>
            <head>ERRATA</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 7. <hi>for</hi> reprove <hi>read</hi> reproach, <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>put out</hi> may, <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>f.</hi> when <hi>r.</hi> what, <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>f.</hi> many <hi>r.</hi> main, <hi>p.</hi> 32. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>put out</hi> be, <hi>p.</hi> 33 <hi>l.</hi> 14 <hi>f.</hi> ſuch <hi>r.</hi> ſay, <hi>p.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 28. <hi>r.</hi> not allow, <hi>p.</hi> 35. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>r.</hi> ſimply, <hi>p.</hi> 39. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>in the margin for</hi> 42 2. <hi>r.</hi> 42. <hi>p</hi> 49 <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 34. <hi>r.</hi> 3. <hi>which ſhould begin the line and ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence, p.</hi> 51. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> premiſe, <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>f.</hi> baptized <hi>r.</hi> lapſed, <hi>p</hi> 60. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>r.</hi> gueſt, <hi>p.</hi> 65. <hi>l.</hi> 27. <hi>f.</hi> the <hi>r.</hi> by, <hi>p.</hi> 67 <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>f.</hi> communication <hi>r.</hi> commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, <hi>p.</hi> 71. <hi>l.</hi> 13 <hi>put a</hi> period <hi>after</hi> worſhip. <hi>p.</hi> 74. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>f.</hi> all <hi>r.</hi> and, <hi>p</hi> 75. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>f.</hi> alſo <hi>r.</hi> and ſo, <hi>p.</hi> 91. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>r.</hi> relation, <hi>p.</hi> 99. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> reference, <hi>p.</hi> 110. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>f.</hi> and Gentiles <hi>r.</hi> aſſembilies, <hi>p.</hi> 116 <hi>l.</hi> 1, 2. <hi>r.</hi> Gilleſpy, <hi>p.</hi> 117. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>put in the margin</hi> 1 Cor. 10.7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>p.</hi> 120 <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>f</hi> principles <hi>r.</hi> priviledges, <hi>p.</hi> 127. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>f.</hi> God <hi>r.</hi> Goſpel, <hi>p.</hi> 151. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>ſ.</hi> no <hi>r</hi> not, <hi>p.</hi> 164. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>ſ</hi> drived <hi>r.</hi> derived, <hi>p.</hi> 173. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>put out the ſtop after</hi> ſenſe.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
